<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Extiri Blog</title>
    <description>blog about Extiri, programming and cybersecurity
</description>
    <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://extiri.com/blog/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 18:46:34 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 18:46:34 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Study Faster with Read-Aloud PDF Apps</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;Studying isn’t just about logging hours - it’s about how effectively you absorb and retain information. Yet, reading through stacks of PDF textbooks, research papers, and study guides can be time-consuming, mentally draining, and difficult to maintain consistently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where &lt;strong&gt;text-to-speech (TTS) apps&lt;/strong&gt; transform your workflow. By converting written content into natural-sounding audio, they let you &lt;strong&gt;listen to PDFs and other study materials while commuting, exercising, or during your evening routine&lt;/strong&gt;. With the right approach, read-aloud technology can turn otherwise wasted time into productive study sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this guide, you’ll discover:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How listening to PDFs supports faster learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why offline, privacy-focused tools matter for students&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practical strategies to integrate read-aloud PDFs into your study routine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How &lt;strong&gt;Chitneek&lt;/strong&gt; helps you study from PDFs anywhere, without internet or privacy concerns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-listening-to-your-study-materials-actually-works&quot;&gt;Why listening to your study materials actually works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional reading requires sustained visual focus, which leads to eye strain and makes it harder to study in non-ideal environments. Listening changes this dynamic completely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study anywhere:&lt;/strong&gt; Convert PDFs to audio and review material while walking to class, cooking dinner, or cleaning your room&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better retention:&lt;/strong&gt; Research shows TTS improves comprehension by engaging multisensory learning - combining visual and auditory processing helps information stick&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible pacing:&lt;/strong&gt; Speed up playback to 1.5x or 2x when reviewing familiar material, or slow down for complex concepts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessibility advantage:&lt;/strong&gt; For students with dyslexia, visual impairments, or reading challenges, TTS removes barriers that make dense PDFs inaccessible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A meta-analysis found that text-to-speech tools showed a meaningful positive effect on reading comprehension for students with reading difficulties, demonstrating this isn’t just a convenience feature - it’s a proven learning tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-formats-you-can-turn-into-audio&quot;&gt;What formats you can turn into audio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PDFs are everywhere in academic life - textbooks, journal articles, lecture slides, assignment briefs. A good TTS app should handle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PDF documents&lt;/strong&gt; – your primary study material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web articles&lt;/strong&gt; – supplementary reading and research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPUB files&lt;/strong&gt; – digital textbooks and study guides&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plain text&lt;/strong&gt; – notes and pasted content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more formats your app supports, the less time you spend converting files or switching between different tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-privacy-matters-cloud-vs-offline-tts&quot;&gt;Why privacy matters: cloud vs. offline TTS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most mainstream TTS apps upload your documents to cloud servers for processing. This raises real concerns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your academic PDFs, research notes, and personal study materials pass through third-party servers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You need constant internet access to use the app&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your reading habits and document content may be tracked or analyzed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slow connections interrupt your study flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offline TTS apps keep everything local.&lt;/strong&gt; Your PDFs never leave your device, you can study anywhere regardless of connectivity, and there’s zero tracking of what you read or when.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For students working with sensitive research, unpublished papers, or simply valuing privacy, offline processing isn’t just a feature - it’s essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meet-chitneek-a-pdf-reader-built-for-learning&quot;&gt;Meet Chitneek: a PDF reader built for learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/chitneek.html&quot;&gt;Chitneek&lt;/a&gt; is designed specifically for students who want to &lt;strong&gt;read aloud PDF files efficiently and privately&lt;/strong&gt;. Unlike cloud-based alternatives, Chitneek processes everything on your device using iOS’s built-in voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why students choose Chitneek:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;True offline functionality:&lt;/strong&gt; Read aloud PDF files with zero internet requirement once saved - perfect for commutes, flights, or anywhere connectivity is limited&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy-first design:&lt;/strong&gt; Files are processed on-device, so your PDFs and reading habits stay completely private&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Natural iOS voices:&lt;/strong&gt; Uses Apple’s built-in voices for clear, consistent narration that sounds natural&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjustable playback:&lt;/strong&gt; Control speech rate and pitch to match your comprehension needs - slow down for difficult research papers, speed up for review&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background listening:&lt;/strong&gt; Keep audio playing while you use other apps, take notes, or browse references&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smart bookmarks:&lt;/strong&gt; Mark important sections to replay difficult material or jump straight to key passages during review&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Format flexibility:&lt;/strong&gt; Import PDFs and EPUBs from Files, share from other apps, paste text, or save web pages to PDF&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stay organized:&lt;/strong&gt; Use named groups to keep your study materials tidy and easy to find&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built-in discovery:&lt;/strong&gt; Find free books from Project Gutenberg and follow RSS feeds directly in the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re working through a 50-page research paper or reviewing lecture notes before an exam, Chitneek lets you study on your terms. A 7-day free trial is available to test both monthly and yearly subscription plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-actually-study-faster-with-read-aloud-pdfs&quot;&gt;How to actually study faster with read-aloud PDFs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just play audio passively. Here’s how to actually learn faster:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pre-read-then-listen&quot;&gt;Pre-read, then listen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skim the PDF first to understand structure and main arguments. Then listen to reinforce and fill gaps in understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-bookmarks-for-key-sections&quot;&gt;Use bookmarks for key sections&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark important passages with Chitneek’s bookmark feature. When reviewing for exams, you can jump straight to the most critical material without scrubbing through audio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;organize-with-named-groups&quot;&gt;Organize with named groups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separate content by subject, priority, or exam date using named groups. This makes finding specific material effortless during review sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;practice-active-recall-while-listening&quot;&gt;Practice active recall while listening&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pause the audio regularly. Summarize what you just heard out loud or write a quick note. This forces your brain to process, not just passively consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;layer-your-learning&quot;&gt;Layer your learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to PDFs during commutes or exercise. Later, sit down and review the same material visually, adding annotations or creating study notes. This dual-mode approach strengthens memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adjust-speed-strategically&quot;&gt;Adjust speed strategically&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First pass on new material: Normal or slightly slower speed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review sessions: 1.5x speed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final pre-exam cramming: 2x speed for familiar content only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Combine with traditional study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Read-aloud PDFs work best as part of a complete study system. Use them for initial exposure and review, but still engage visually with complex diagrams, equations, or tables that don’t convert well to audio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-tts-cant-do-and-what-to-do-instead&quot;&gt;What TTS can’t do (and what to do instead)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be realistic about limitations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex layouts suffer:&lt;/strong&gt; Tables, mathematical equations, and multi-column formats often read awkwardly. You’ll need to review these sections visually in the original PDF.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagrams and images:&lt;/strong&gt; TTS can’t describe figures. Keep the PDF open to glance at visual elements when referenced.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organization matters:&lt;/strong&gt; Without using groups or clear naming, finding specific content later becomes frustrating. Spend a few minutes organizing files upfront.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution:&lt;/strong&gt; Use TTS for prose-heavy content (textbook chapters, research papers, articles). Study graphs, charts, and equations separately with traditional reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ready-to-turn-your-pdfs-into-audio&quot;&gt;Ready to turn your PDFs into audio?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text-to-speech apps transform how efficiently you can study by &lt;strong&gt;turning idle time into productive learning time&lt;/strong&gt;. By listening to read-aloud PDFs during your daily routine, you can cover more material, reinforce retention, and maintain momentum even when sitting down to read isn’t practical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a tool that reads PDFs aloud without compromising your privacy, &lt;strong&gt;Chitneek&lt;/strong&gt; delivers on-device processing, natural iOS voices, and the flexibility students need. No cloud uploads, no tracking, no accounts required - just your PDFs converted to audio, ready whenever you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start studying smarter by making every moment count. Try Chitneek’s 7-day free trial and experience what it’s like to have your entire PDF library accessible as audio, anywhere you go. Learn more &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/chitneek.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/pl/app/chitneek-read-aloud/id6749827870&quot;&gt;download now&lt;/a&gt; from the App Store on iOS.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/how-to-study-read-aloud-pdf</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/how-to-study-read-aloud-pdf</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>study-guide</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ranking of The Best Snippet Managers for Mac 2025</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;As developers, we all face the same problem: brilliant ideas scattered across chat logs, forgotten code experiments buried in old projects, and that perfect solution you swear you wrote last month but can’t find anywhere. Your code snippets deserve better than living in chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mac ecosystem offers several solid snippet managers, each with its own philosophy. Let’s look at what’s out there and help you find the right fit for your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-contenders&quot;&gt;The Contenders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snippetslab-the-traditional-choice&quot;&gt;SnippetsLab: The Traditional Choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.renfei.org/snippets-lab/images/Landing/hero2.webp&quot; alt=&quot;SnippetsLab Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SnippetsLab has been around since 2015 and became completely free in November 2024. It’s a polished, Mac-native snippet manager that does one thing well: organizing code snippets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; The interface is clean and developer-focused. With support for over 580 languages, multi-level folders, tags, and smart groups, it offers solid organizational tools. The menubar assistant gives you quick access without opening the main window, and iCloud sync works reliably across Macs. The Markdown support is comprehensive, including Mermaid diagrams and LaTeX formulas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; SnippetsLab is strictly a snippet organizer - nothing more. There’s no iOS version, no AI features, no automation beyond basic organization. If you need parameterized templates or want to inject dynamic data into your snippets, you’ll need to look elsewhere. It’s Mac-only, and while the GitHub Gist integration exists, it’s one-way for exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Developers who want a straightforward, free snippet library without bells and whistles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snippety-the-text-expansion-specialist&quot;&gt;Snippety: The Text Expansion Specialist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://snippety.app/images/app-main-screen-new.png&quot; alt=&quot;Snippety App&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snippety ($24.99 one-time purchase) positions itself as a productivity tool with a focus on text expansion and automation across macOS, iOS, and iPadOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; The snippet expander feature is excellent - type your keyword and your snippet appears instantly without opening the app. It supports 50+ languages with syntax highlighting, nearly 250 themes, and includes 19 smart placeholders for dynamic content like dates, AI-assisted text (via OpenAI API or custom providers), and command-line scripts. The iOS and iPadOS companion app with a custom keyboard is genuinely useful, and iCloud sync keeps everything synchronized across Apple devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; While Snippety excels at text expansion and has AI integration through OpenAI’s API, it’s primarily designed for rapid text insertion rather than building a comprehensive knowledge base. The organizational structure is simpler compared to dedicated snippet managers. It’s also Apple-exclusive - no Windows or Linux support if you work across platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Apple users who want fast text expansion with cross-device access and don’t mind a one-time purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snipperapp-2-the-github-gist-integration-champion&quot;&gt;SnipperApp 2: The GitHub Gist Integration Champion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://snipperapp.com/static/add34ebf75c8b45d46ca17d2d94df70f/337b1/app-v211-light.webp&quot; alt=&quot;SnipperApp 2 Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SnipperApp 2 (free with subscription options) is a native Swift-based snippet manager designed specifically for developers who live in the GitHub ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; Full GitHub Gist integration is the standout feature - sync, edit, and manage your gists directly from the app. With 120+ programming languages supported, the editor includes all the essentials: syntax highlighting, line numbers, invisible character display, and tab size customization. It supports multiple storage options (local, iCloud, GitHub), works offline-first, and includes Markdown preview mode. The ability to share snippets via secret links is handy for quick collaboration. Image attachments, tags, folders with drag-and-drop, and backup/restore functionality round out a solid feature set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s Mac-only with no iOS companion app. The subscription model ($3.99 monthly, $19.99 annual, or $39.99 lifetime) may not appeal to everyone, especially with free alternatives available. While feature-rich for code management, it lacks advanced automation, AI features, or dynamic templates. The interface, while functional, is more utilitarian than modern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Developers heavily invested in GitHub Gist who want a dedicated Mac app for managing their gists with proper organization and offline support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;masscode-the-open-source-alternative&quot;&gt;massCode: The Open-Source Alternative&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://masscode.io/preview.png&quot; alt=&quot;massCode Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;massCode is completely free and open-source, built with Electron, Vue, and CodeMirror for cross-platform compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s free, period. Multi-level folders, tags, and fragments (tabs within snippets) provide decent organization. CodeMirror powers the editor with support for 160+ grammars out of the box (600+ available through .tmLanguage files). The HTML/CSS preview feature is handy for front-end work, Markdown support includes Mermaid diagrams, and there’s even a presentation mode for turning snippets into slideshows. It works on Windows, Linux, and macOS, and being open-source means community contributions drive development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; No built-in sync - you’ll need to manually set up a cloud folder if you want cross-device access. The Electron foundation means it’s heavier on system resources than native apps. While feature-rich, the interface can feel less polished than commercial alternatives. AI features and advanced automation are absent, and being community-driven means feature development can be unpredictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Developers who value open-source software and need cross-platform support without spending money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clipguru-the-lightweight-mobile-first-choice&quot;&gt;ClipGuru: The Lightweight Mobile-First Choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/main-screen-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;ClipGuru Interface&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru is a lightweight clipboard manager that works seamlessly across iOS, iPadOS, and macOS, designed for quick capture and easy retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; The interface is beautifully simple and native to Apple platforms. Save text, links, and images with one tap, and the smart search makes finding anything instant. The custom keyboard extension lets you access your clips from any app without switching contexts - perfect for rapid workflows. The share extension works from Safari and other apps, making it effortless to collect research, quotes, and URLs. With support for Apple Vision Pro and requiring only iOS 17.6+, it’s built for modern Apple devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; ClipGuru is intentionally lightweight, which means it lacks advanced features like syntax highlighting for code, dynamic templates, or automation. The free version saves only 4 clips (unlimited with Pro upgrade for ~$1.25). There’s no AI features, no parameterized templates, and no advanced organizational structures beyond tags. It’s Apple ecosystem only - no Windows or Linux support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Apple users who want a simple, fast, mobile-friendly clipboard manager that syncs across devices without complexity. Ideal for non-developers or those who prioritize simplicity over power features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;codemenu-your-augmented-memory&quot;&gt;CodeMenu: Your Augmented Memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/codemenu-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;CodeMenu Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CodeMenu takes a different approach entirely. It’s not just a snippet manager - it’s designed to be your external memory system for everything that fuels your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What makes it different:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beyond code snippets:&lt;/strong&gt; While SnippetsLab, Snippety, SnipperApp, and massCode focus primarily on code and text snippets, CodeMenu recognizes that developers work with diverse content. Store color palettes, design notes, AI prompts, screenshots, research, and visual references alongside your code. Everything gets rich descriptions with Markdown, LaTeX, images, and diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Truly local-first with intelligence:&lt;/strong&gt; Your library stays completely local and works offline by default. Unlike tools that require cloud services or external APIs, CodeMenu includes on-device AI features (generation, chat, semantic search) that run securely on your Mac. You only share what you choose through the optional Snippets Store or team sync.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context-aware suggestions:&lt;/strong&gt; The Suggestions app (available on GitHub) surfaces relevant snippets based on what you’re working on, learning from your patterns without sending data anywhere. It’s like having an assistant that remembers everything you’ve ever saved and knows when you need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built-in productivity tools:&lt;/strong&gt; Why switch between apps? CodeMenu bundles editors, converters, mock data generators, a RegEx tester, and a code-to-image creator. It’s designed to minimize context switching during rapid prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parameterized templates that adapt:&lt;/strong&gt; Unlike static snippets, CodeMenu templates inject live data - current date, shell outputs, user input. One saved fragment morphs to fit any scenario. Combined with the HTTP API and JavaScript automation (with extensive API documentation), you can integrate CodeMenu into your existing workflows deeply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real extensibility:&lt;/strong&gt; Extensions for the Suggestions system, JavaScript automation with CLI support for any language, HTTP API, and comprehensive documentation at docs.extiri.com mean you can bend CodeMenu to your exact needs. It’s not just a storage box - it’s programmable infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where CodeMenu shines uniquely:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While SnippetsLab offers clean organization, Snippety provides fast text expansion, SnipperApp excels at GitHub Gist management, massCode gives you free cross-platform access, and ClipGuru delivers mobile-first simplicity, CodeMenu is the only one that combines local-first privacy, on-device AI, visual content management, and true extensibility into a cohesive system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a developer, designer, or creator who works with diverse content types and wants a personal knowledge system that remembers everything while respecting your privacy, CodeMenu is built for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Professionals who need a comprehensive personal knowledge base that’s intelligent, extensible, and completely under their control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feature-comparison&quot;&gt;Feature Comparison&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how these tools stack up across key capabilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Feature&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;ClipGuru&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;SnippetsLab&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Snippety&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;SnipperApp 2&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;massCode&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Syntax Highlighting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;60+ languages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;580+ languages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50+ languages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;120+ languages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;160+ (600+ available)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-Platform&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mac only&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;macOS, iOS, iPadOS, Vision&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mac only&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;macOS, iOS, iPadOS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mac only&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mac, Windows, Linux&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (on-device: generation, chat, search)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (OpenAI/Ollama API)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dynamic Templates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (parameterized)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (19 placeholders)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visual Content&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (images, colors, screenshots)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (images, links)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (images, files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (images)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offline-First&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (fully local)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (optional iCloud)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (optional iCloud)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (iCloud sync)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (offline-first)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (no built-in sync)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text Expansion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (abbreviations)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (menubar)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (primary feature)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built-in Utilities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (editors, converters, RegEx)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (HTML preview, slides)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub Integration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (Gist export)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (full Gist sync)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyboard Extension&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share Extension&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (JS + HTTP server)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (scripts)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (sync + Store)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (iCloud)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (secret links)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Manual sharing&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Markdown + LaTeX&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (+ Mermaid)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (preview)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (+ Mermaid)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pricing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$29.99 one-time / $3.99 monthly (7-day free trial)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free (4 clips) / ~$1.25 Pro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$24.99 one-time&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free / $3.99 monthly / $19.99 annual / $39.99 lifetime&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free (open-source)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pricing for United States (ClipGuru Pro in PLN ≈ $1.25 USD)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bottom-line&quot;&gt;The Bottom Line&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choosing a snippet manager depends on what you actually need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ClipGuru&lt;/strong&gt; if you want a simple, mobile-first clipboard manager that works beautifully across Apple devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SnippetsLab&lt;/strong&gt; if you want a free, focused code snippet organizer with no frills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snippety&lt;/strong&gt; if text expansion speed across Apple devices is your priority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SnipperApp 2&lt;/strong&gt; if you live in GitHub Gists and want native Mac management with offline support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;massCode&lt;/strong&gt; if you need free, open-source, cross-platform compatibility&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt; if you want an intelligent, extensible personal knowledge system that handles everything from code to design to research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best snippet manager isn’t about feature checklists - it’s about matching your workflow. Traditional snippet managers organize what you’ve saved. ClipGuru keeps your clipboard accessible across devices. SnipperApp bridges your local work with GitHub. CodeMenu becomes the thinking partner that helps you remember, discover, and ship better work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your ideas deserve a home that works as hard as you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ready to try our apps?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ClipGuru&lt;/strong&gt;: Available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/pl/app/clipguru/id6753787446&quot;&gt;App Store&lt;/a&gt; for iOS, iPadOS, and macOS. Free with optional Pro upgrade. Visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/clipguru&quot;&gt;extiri.com/clipguru&lt;/a&gt; to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt;: Available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/codemenu-snippet-manager/id1583463781?mt=12&quot;&gt;Mac App Store&lt;/a&gt; with a 7-day free trial, or purchase a one-time license. Visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/codemenu.html&quot;&gt;extiri.com/codemenu&lt;/a&gt; to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; For official screenshots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ClipGuru&lt;/strong&gt;: Visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/clipguru&quot;&gt;extiri.com/clipguru&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/pl/app/clipguru/id6753787446&quot;&gt;App Store page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SnippetsLab&lt;/strong&gt;: Visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.renfei.org/snippets-lab/&quot;&gt;renfei.org/snippets-lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snippety&lt;/strong&gt;: Visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://snippety.app/&quot;&gt;snippety.app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SnipperApp 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://snipperapp.com/&quot;&gt;snipperapp.com&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/snipperapp-2/id1469182443?mt=12&quot;&gt;Mac App Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;massCode&lt;/strong&gt;: Visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://masscode.io/&quot;&gt;masscode.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt;: Visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/codemenu-snippet-manager/id1583463781?mt=12&quot;&gt;Mac App Store page&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/codemenu.html&quot;&gt;extiri.com/codemenu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/the-best-snippet-manager</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/the-best-snippet-manager</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introducing ClipGuru — a lightweight clipboard manager</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;ClipGuru is a small, mobile-first clipboard manager built for iPhone and iPad. It solves a simple problem: when you copy something important on your device, you should be able to save it and find it again. Add clips quickly by tapping Paste inside the app or by typing a new clip — saved items are then easy to search and reuse. The macOS app complements the mobile experience for when you’re on a desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all been there — on your phone or tablet you copy a quick link or quote, then later it’s gone because you copied something else. ClipGuru gives you a simple place to save those items: tap Paste in the app (or enter the content) to add it to your ClipGuru history. Once saved, clips are searchable and ready to reuse across your devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/main-screen-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Main screen&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-is-clipguru-for&quot;&gt;Who is ClipGuru for?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru is for anyone who copies things a lot: writers, developers, designers, students, researchers, and people who simply like to keep small pieces of information handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Researching an article: copy quotes, links, facts, and find them later without opening dozens of tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design work: copy screenshots or small assets to reuse in presentations and mockups.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multi-device workflow: copy on iPad, paste on Mac, continue your work uninterrupted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-makes-clipguru-different&quot;&gt;What makes ClipGuru different?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/keyboard-in-messages-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Keyboard in messages&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lightweight and focused: it does one job well — store and retrieve clipboard items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fast search: find past clips by keyword in seconds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multi-device friendly: saved clips sync across your devices via iCloud — add a clip on your iPhone or iPad and it will appear on your other devices (macOS included) shortly after.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Special keyboard: thanks to a custom keyboard you can access snippets anywhere you need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quick review: review your snippets and decide whether you want to keep or delete them without distractions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;find-snippets-quicker&quot;&gt;Find snippets quicker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/semantic-search-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Semantic search&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever copied five different things in a row and needed the third one? ClipGuru helps you avoid clipboard roulette: paste items into the app as you go, then search by keyword to find them instantly. Results are fast and support simple filters so you can narrow results quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keep-your-favorites-close&quot;&gt;Keep your favorites close&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some clips matter more than others — a signature line, a frequently shared link, or a small image you reuse. Pin those items to keep them at the top of your list so they’re one tap away when you need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lightweight-by-design&quot;&gt;Lightweight by design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru intentionally avoids feature bloat. No complex tagging systems or heavy UIs — just a clean history, favorites, and fast search. It’s designed to help without getting in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;room-to-grow&quot;&gt;Room to grow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/review-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Review&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial release focuses on the essentials. We’ll add features based on feedback, but the core promise remains: a small, reliable place to save and find the clips you care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru offers a simple, no-fuss approach to clipboard management. If you often copy things and want a reliable way to save and reuse them across devices, ClipGuru is built for that. Try it on your phone or tablet and see how it fits into your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re keeping the initial release simple and iterating based on feedback. If you have ideas or workflows you’d love ClipGuru to support, tell us — we’re listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru is available on iPhone, iPad, and Mac. Try it and let your clipboard finally work for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, give it a try on your phone or tablet — see how it fits into your mobile workflow and let your clips work for you. ClipGuru stores &lt;strong&gt;text&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;links&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;images&lt;/strong&gt; that you add. Paste into the app (tap Paste) on iPhone or iPad to add a clip; saved clips sync via iCloud and will be available on your other devices, including the macOS companion app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because honestly, we’ve all got better things to do than hunt for that thing we copied five minutes ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-get-started&quot;&gt;Lets get started&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download ClipGuru from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/pl/app/clipguru/id6753787446&quot;&gt;App Store&lt;/a&gt;. The app is mobile-first (iPhone and iPad) but it’s also available on macOS. Learn more &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/clipguru.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/introducing-clipguru</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/introducing-clipguru</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Best Dev Habits to Save Time Every Day: Using Boilerplate, Snippets, and Templates</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a common misconception that productive developers are the ones who type the fastest or memorize the most syntax. In reality, the developers who consistently ship quality work and never seem stressed aren’t necessarily working harder—they’re working smarter by eliminating friction from their daily routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about your own workflow for a second. How much time do you spend recreating the same boilerplate? Looking up commands you’ve run a thousand times? Switching between your editor, browser tabs, and terminal just to find that one piece of documentation? These tiny interruptions don’t feel like much in the moment, but they compound throughout the day, leaving you exhausted by 3 PM even though you feel like you haven’t accomplished much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The developers who’ve figured this out—the ones who seem to breeze through complex projects—aren’t relying on tricks or shortcuts. They’re leaning on &lt;strong&gt;habits&lt;/strong&gt; that remove these daily friction points. They reuse patterns that work. They automate the repetitive stuff. They keep their tools organized and sharp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news? These aren’t secret techniques that take years to master. They’re practical habits you can start adopting today. Some will save you five minutes here and there. Others will save you hours every week. Together, they compound into a workflow that feels effortless and keeps you focused on actually solving problems instead of fighting your environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are &lt;strong&gt;10 habits&lt;/strong&gt; that will genuinely save you time every single day. Pick a couple to start with, make them stick, then add more. You don’t need to overhaul your entire workflow overnight—small improvements add up faster than you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-build-and-use-a-snippet-library&quot;&gt;1. Build and Use a Snippet Library&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Rewriting the same error handlers, validation, or logging patterns eats up time and introduces inconsistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Save these patterns into a snippet library. Tag them by language (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;js&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;py&lt;/code&gt;) or domain (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;db&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;auth&lt;/code&gt;) so you can recall them instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# ${your_code_here}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;logger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Error: {e}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; Tools like &lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt; make searching and inserting these snippets lightning fast—without breaking flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-standardize-with-templates&quot;&gt;2. Standardize with Templates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Every new module or component starts with the same boilerplate. Doing it by hand is wasted effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Use templates for React components, API routes, or unit tests. You’ll save setup time and keep your codebase consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example React template:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-javascript highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;React&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&apos;react&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;default&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ComponentName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}({})&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;div&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ComponentName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;works&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sr&quot;&gt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Store it once → reuse it forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-automate-file-and-folder-creation&quot;&gt;3. Automate File and Folder Creation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Creating directories, configs, and starter files manually slows you down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Use CLI generators (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ng generate component&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rails g scaffold&lt;/code&gt;) or pair templates with a snippet tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; Keep your templates in CodeMenu, then paste them wherever needed—no need to memorize every CLI flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-document-as-you-go&quot;&gt;4. Document as You Go&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Leaving documentation for “later” often means it never happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Write docstrings, inline comments, or README snippets at the same time you write code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example in Python:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;calculate_tax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;amount&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;
    Calculate tax for a given amount.
    Args:
        amount (float): The income or purchase amount.
    Returns:
        float: The tax due.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bonus: Save comment/docstring templates as snippets so you always follow the same structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-master-keyboard-shortcuts&quot;&gt;5. Master Keyboard Shortcuts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Every time you reach for the mouse, you lose momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Learn IDE, terminal, and snippet manager shortcuts. Add one new shortcut to your muscle memory each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VS Code: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Cmd+Shift+P&lt;/code&gt; → open command palette.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CodeMenu: Global shortcut → instant snippet search, no window-switching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-reuse-proven-solutions&quot;&gt;6. Reuse Proven Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Developers often re-solve problems they’ve already cracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Before coding, ask:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did I solve this before?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there a library or snippet that covers it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you find a solid solution, add it to your snippet/tooling library so you never waste that effort again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-keep-your-tools-organized&quot;&gt;7. Keep Your Tools Organized&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; A messy library (snippets, bookmarks, repos) makes tools harder to use, so you stop using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Spend 10 minutes weekly organizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tag snippets (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;validation&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;db&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delete duplicates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rename cryptic titles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CodeMenu, this takes minutes, and pays off every time you search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-batch-small-tasks&quot;&gt;8. Batch Small Tasks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Context switching kills flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Collect small tasks into a batch list. Handle them in one block instead of sprinkling them through your deep-work hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Answer 5 PR comments together.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write all TODO cleanups before stand-up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update snippets at the end of the week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-version-your-snippets&quot;&gt;9. Version Your Snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Snippets evolve over time. Without versioning, teams diverge into conflicting patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Store shared snippets in Git or a snippet server. Review changes like normal code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tooling:&lt;/strong&gt; Extiri’s &lt;strong&gt;Snippets Store&lt;/strong&gt; (self-hostable) works well with CodeMenu, giving your team one source of truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-schedule-productivity-maintenance&quot;&gt;10. Schedule “Productivity Maintenance”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Your workflow gets bloated unless you prune and refine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Once a week, spend 15 minutes maintaining:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delete unused snippets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve one template.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn a new shortcut.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean up your workspace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of it as “spring cleaning” for your dev environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving time as a developer comes down to habits you repeat daily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a snippet library&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standardize with templates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automate setup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Document as you go&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reuse solutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay organized&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Batch tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Version snippets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maintain weekly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👉 Start with 2 habits this week. Once they’re second nature, add more. Small improvements compound into hours saved every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a tool to make snippets and templates painless, give &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/codemenu.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a try—it turns many of these habits into effortless defaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-day-starter-checklist-do-one-per-day&quot;&gt;7-day starter checklist (do one per day)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1: Save three snippets you use daily into your snippet manager and tag them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 2: Create one template for a common file type (React component, test file, or module).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 3: Add a keyboard shortcut for your snippet manager to insert snippets without leaving the editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 4: Batch three small tasks and handle them in one focused block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 5: Audit your snippet library for duplicates and rename unclear items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 6: Version one snippet in Git (or export your snippet tool library) so it’s tracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 7: Teach a teammate one shortcut or snippet workflow (sharing solidifies habit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note on tooling: the suggestions above work with many snippet tools; CodeMenu is one example that supports quick insertion and tagging—feel free to substitute your preferred tool.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/ten-developer-habits</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/ten-developer-habits</guid>
        
        <category>productivity</category>
        
        <category>snippets</category>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introducing Chitneek for iOS - Hear Your Documents, Simply and Privately</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;Do you want a reading app that’s clean, reliable, and doesn’t force you to sign up for everything? Meet &lt;strong&gt;Chitneek&lt;/strong&gt;, the iPhone app that turns PDFs, EPUBs, web pages, notes, Gutenberg classics, and RSS feeds into spoken text — without cloud uploads or unnecessary complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-can-do-with-chitneek&quot;&gt;What You Can Do with Chitneek&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/chitneek-screenshots/Screenshot-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Read PDFs, EPUBs, websites and text&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listen to PDFs, EPUBs, and notes&lt;/strong&gt; using native iOS text-to-speech voices — nothing fancy needed, just clear and dependable reading.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Convert text or web pages into PDFs&lt;/strong&gt; so you can listen later whenever it suits you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access Project Gutenberg right inside the app&lt;/strong&gt; — public domain books are just a tap away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subscribe to RSS feeds&lt;/strong&gt; and have the latest posts delivered for you to listen to.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organize your library&lt;/strong&gt; with named groups, and bookmarks so you can easily find where you left off.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customize playback&lt;/strong&gt;: adjust speed and pitch per document or book to match your listening style.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CarPlay integration&lt;/strong&gt; so you can keep your eyes on the road while listening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep timer&lt;/strong&gt; to stop playback automatically — perfect for nighttime listening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All local storage &amp;amp; usage&lt;/strong&gt;: your files remain on your device; you’re in control of your data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-chitneek-special&quot;&gt;What Makes Chitneek Special&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/chitneek-screenshots/Screenshot-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Keep you collection organized&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitneek isn’t trying to be every kind of reader-app out there — instead, it focuses on doing a few things very well, in a way that feels natural:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimal friction, maximum focus&lt;/strong&gt; — no signups, no cloud dependencies, no uploading.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built-in sources&lt;/strong&gt; like Gutenberg and RSS reduce manual importing and help you access content you care about faster.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple yet powerful organization&lt;/strong&gt; with groups and bookmarks — because locating what you want should be quick.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible audio controls&lt;/strong&gt; which can be adapted to your listening pace and preference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy and peace of mind&lt;/strong&gt; — your documents stay yours, stored locally. No mystery about where your text goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-youll-want-chitneek&quot;&gt;Why You’ll Want Chitneek&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/chitneek-screenshots/Screenshot-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Listen to blog feeds&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of these sound familiar, Chitneek may be exactly what you’ve been looking for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You read often, but want to rest your eyes — or want to listen during walks, commuting, or chores.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You follow blogs or websites and wish for hands-free listening to new content.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You love classic books or public domain works and want easy access without hunting for files.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You care about privacy, offline reliability, and simplicity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-started&quot;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/chitneek-screenshots/Screenshot-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Find interesting books quickly&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download &lt;strong&gt;Chitneek — Read Aloud&lt;/strong&gt; from the App Store.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open the app.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Browse Gutenberg works or add RSS feeds. Import any PDFs or EPUBs you already have.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tap to play, adjust speed/pitch, use the sleep timer or CarPlay when needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organize using groups to keep things tidy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitneek is for anyone who believes that reading aloud should be easy, private, and dependable. If you’ve been looking for a calm, uncluttered experience that still covers everything essential — this is it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/introducing-chitneek</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/introducing-chitneek</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From Theory to Practice: 5 Platforms That Turn Learning Into Doing</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;Ever feel stuck in &lt;em&gt;tutorial hell&lt;/em&gt; - watching endless videos but never actually applying what you learn? I’ve been there too. Books and courses are fantastic - they give structure, context, and explanations - but real understanding often comes when you &lt;em&gt;actually do it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, I’ve discovered several platforms that take concepts from theory to hands-on experience. Each one is free and ready to help you practice and internalize what you learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-cryptohack--experiment-with-cryptography&quot;&gt;1. CryptoHack – Experiment with Cryptography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/cryptohack-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;CryptoHack&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cryptography has always fascinated me. Recently, I wanted a way to practice it beyond reading theory, and that’s when I found &lt;strong&gt;CryptoHack&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CryptoHack offers challenges that let you experiment directly with cryptographic algorithms. From XOR operations to RSA attacks, you get to see how the theory works in practice. They also have structured introductory courses if you want guided learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptohack.org&quot;&gt;Explore CryptoHack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-iximiuz-labs--hands-on-devops&quot;&gt;2. iximiuz Labs – Hands-On DevOps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/ixizmuz-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;iximiuz Labs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often learn Linux or Docker from blogs or books - but the moment it clicks is when I actually spin it up. That’s where &lt;strong&gt;iximiuz Labs&lt;/strong&gt; comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This platform provides practical challenges in Linux, Docker, and Kubernetes. Each challenge is designed to let you solve real-world tasks, deepening your understanding of the concepts while keeping it safe in a sandboxed environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://labs.iximiuz.com/challenges&quot;&gt;Try iximiuz Labs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-deep-ml--understand-machine-learning-from-the-inside&quot;&gt;3. Deep-ML – Understand Machine Learning From the Inside&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/deepml-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Deep-ML&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about PCA, neural networks, or gradient descent is one thing - but implementing them yourself is where understanding solidifies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deep-ML&lt;/strong&gt; offers machine learning and deep learning challenges crafted to make you code the algorithms yourself. It’s a structured playground that helps you see how the math and theory translate into real computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deep-ml.com&quot;&gt;Start with Deep-ML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-webgpu-puzzles--feel-parallel-execution&quot;&gt;4. WebGPU Puzzles – Feel Parallel Execution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/wgpupuzzles-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;WebGPU Puzzles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GPU programming can feel abstract until you run code yourself. &lt;strong&gt;WebGPU Puzzles&lt;/strong&gt; brings WGSL coding directly to your browser, no installation required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through small compute puzzles, you dispatch GPU threads and see parallel execution in action. It’s a surprisingly intuitive way to get a tactile feel for GPU computing fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gpupuzzles.answer.ai&quot;&gt;Explore WebGPU Puzzles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-project-euler--sharpen-your-mathematical-thinking&quot;&gt;5. Project Euler – Sharpen Your Mathematical Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/projecteuler-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Project Euler&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about algorithms is useful - but solving them is transformative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Euler&lt;/strong&gt; offers small, elegant math-and-programming problems that make you think algorithmically. I use it especially to train my mathematical thinking, and each solved problem feels like a small victory that reinforces the concepts I’ve learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://projecteuler.net&quot;&gt;Try Project Euler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hands-on-learning-matters&quot;&gt;Hands-On Learning Matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books, blogs, and courses give you the foundation. Hands-on practice turns that knowledge into skill. These platforms have helped me solidify concepts, see results instantly, and stay motivated by giving tangible accomplishments along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope they do the same for you. Dive in, experiment, fail, fix, and learn - your brain will thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/from-theory-to-practice</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/from-theory-to-practice</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>studying</category>
        
        <category>resources</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>10 Reason to Use a Snippet Manager in the AI Era</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;With AI tools like ChatGPT, Claude, and GitHub Copilot revolutionizing the way we code, it’s easy to wonder if traditional tools like snippet managers are still relevant. The short answer? Absolutely. A snippet manager remains a critical part of a modern developer’s workflow, providing organization, precision, and efficiency that perfectly complements the power of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how a snippet manager like CodeMenu can supercharge your productivity—especially when paired with AI-driven tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-instant-access-to-frequently-used-code&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Instant Access to Frequently Used Code&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI is fantastic for generating code snippets on demand, but it might not always produce exactly what you need. A snippet manager saves you from having to tweak AI-generated code by providing quick access to your polished, battle-tested snippets. When speed and accuracy matter, having your go-to solutions on hand is invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-organize-code-across-projects&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Organize Code Across Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI tools like GitHub Copilot assist in writing code but don’t inherently organize it. A snippet manager acts as a central hub for managing reusable components, categorized by language, tags, or use case. It ensures that even when you switch projects, your resources are always at your fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-simplify-debugging-with-reusable-solutions&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Simplify Debugging with Reusable Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI can help you debug code, but when dealing with recurring bugs or patterns, snippet managers shine. They let you store and reuse proven debugging snippets, ensuring consistency and saving you from re-inventing the wheel each time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-accelerate-onboarding&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Accelerate Onboarding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While AI can explain code and generate examples, snippet managers provide structured, reusable resources for onboarding. Sharing libraries of pre-approved snippets ensures new team members align with established standards and best practices from day one. AI and snippet managers together can make onboarding faster and more effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-automate-repetitive-tasks&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Automate Repetitive Tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snippet managers with placeholder support allow you to automate repetitive coding tasks with precision. While AI is adept at generating code for dynamic scenarios, snippet managers excel in predictable, repeatable contexts where consistency is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6-boost-creativity-with-built-in-inspiration&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Boost Creativity with Built-In Inspiration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI tools are powerful sources of inspiration, generating new ideas and approaches. A snippet manager complements this by acting as a repository for AI-generated snippets you find useful, allowing you to save, refine, and reuse them for future projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;7-integrate-with-your-tools&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Integrate with Your Tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern snippet managers integrate seamlessly with code editors, browsers, and other tools in your workflow. While AI tools like GitHub Copilot focus on real-time assistance, snippet managers enhance this by providing pre-saved, ready-to-use snippets without disrupting your flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;8-save-time-with-ai-powered-features&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Save Time with AI-Powered Features&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many snippet managers, like CodeMenu, are embracing AI themselves. Features like natural language search and auto-generation of titles make it easier than ever to find and manage your snippets. Unlike cloud-based AI tools, these features often run offline, offering privacy and speed while keeping you in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;9-experiment-and-learn-with-built-in-test-environments&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Experiment and Learn with Built-In Test Environments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI tools assist in prototyping and debugging, but a snippet manager with a built-in test environment offers a sandbox for refining snippets before storing them. This ensures your reusable code is clean, efficient, and ready for deployment whenever you need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;10-beyond-code-store-diverse-assets&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Beyond Code: Store Diverse Assets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI tools specialize in code generation, but snippet managers go beyond by letting you store Markdown templates, AI prompts, color palettes, and more. They become a multi-purpose hub for all your digital assets, making them indispensable for developers, designers, and creators alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-snippet-managers-are-essential-in-the-ai-era&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Snippet Managers Are Essential in the AI Era&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI tools like ChatGPT and GitHub Copilot are undeniably transformative, but they’re not replacements for snippet managers. Instead, they’re complementary. AI thrives in dynamic, exploratory tasks, while snippet managers excel in organization, precision, and repeatability. Together, they create a balanced workflow that boosts both creativity and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By integrating a powerful snippet manager like CodeMenu into your toolkit, you can leverage the strengths of both AI and human organization. CodeMenu’s features—like placeholders, offline AI functions, and support for 55+ languages ensure you’re ready to handle whatever challenges come your way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/ten-reason-to-use-a-snippet-manager-in-the-ai-era</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/ten-reason-to-use-a-snippet-manager-in-the-ai-era</guid>
        
        <category>artificial-intelligence</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building Your Personal Knowledge Base</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;In the age of information overload, managing knowledge effectively is not just a luxury; it’s a necessity. Whether you’re a programmer, writer, researcher, or just someone keen on self-improvement, building a personal knowledge base can transform your efficiency and creativity. Here’s how personal databases like snippet managers can become your secret weapon in this endeavor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;centralization-of-information&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Centralization of Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine all your useful code snippets, notes, bookmarks, and bits of wisdom in one place. Personal databases like CodeMenu allow you to store various types of content—code, images, Markdown, AI prompts—under one roof. This centralization reduces the time you spend hunting for that one snippet you wrote last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;enhanced-retrieval&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhanced Retrieval&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With features like natural language search, tags, and categories, finding what you need becomes quicker. CodeMenu, for example, lets you search snippets not just by keyword but by conceptual relevance, thanks to AI assistance. This means you can find a JavaScript function to manipulate strings by asking for it in plain English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;context-preservation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context Preservation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, the context in which you saved a snippet is as important as the snippet itself. Personal databases allow you to add notes, tags, and descriptions to each item. Over time, this builds a rich tapestry of your thought process, making revisiting old ideas not just possible but insightful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;customization-for-your-workflow&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customization for Your Workflow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every professional or hobbyist has their own workflow. Personal databases can be molded to fit yours. You can create shortcuts, bind snippets to specific applications or contexts, or even automate tasks. For instance, with CodeMenu, you can drag and drop snippets directly into your editor or use abbreviations for on-the-fly replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning-and-growth&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning and Growth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you add to your personal database, you’re not just storing information; you’re documenting your learning journey. Each snippet, note, or image can serve as a reminder of what you’ve learned or as a stepping stone for future explorations. This aspect of personal databases fosters both retention and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;privacy-and-control&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy and Control&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With tools like CodeMenu running many operations offline, you maintain control over your data. Privacy is paramount, especially when dealing with proprietary code or sensitive personal notes. Your knowledge base remains yours, accessible and secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;integration-with-ai&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration with AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern snippet managers integrate AI to not only help you find and organize snippets but also to generate new ones or convert images to code. This AI augmentation can make complex tasks simpler and inspire new ways to work or solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;future-proofing-your-knowledge&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future-Proofing Your Knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As technologies and methodologies evolve, so does your need to adapt. A personal database helps you keep up. You can revisit, update, or delete snippets, ensuring your knowledge base remains relevant and useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a personal knowledge base isn’t just about hoarding information; it’s about crafting a dynamic, ever-evolving tool that grows with you. Tools like Obsidian, Roam Research and CodeMenu empower you to weave all strands of your digital life into a coherent, powerful tool for personal and professional growth. Whether you’re coding, writing, designing, or learning, your personal database is your ally in mastering the information age.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/building-your-personal-knowledge-base</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/building-your-personal-knowledge-base</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Power of Automation - Useful Tools For Automating</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;As developers, we’re often tasked with repetitive, time-consuming activities that can sap creativity and productivity. The good news? Many of these tasks can be automated, freeing up your time to focus on solving real problems and building innovative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automation is no longer a luxury—it’s a necessity in modern software development. Here are 10 tasks every developer should consider automating today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-running-tests-and-deployments-with-cicd-pipelines&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Running Tests and Deployments with CI/CD Pipelines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuous Integration and Continuous Deployment (CI/CD) tools like GitHub Actions, Jenkins, and CircleCI ensure your code is always tested and ready to ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Running unit, integration, and end-to-end tests on every commit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building and deploying code to staging or production environments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rolling back changes if a deployment fails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Catch bugs early and deploy faster without manual intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-code-formatting-and-linting&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Code Formatting and Linting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inconsistent formatting can lead to wasted time during code reviews. Tools like Prettier, ESLint, Black, or clang-format can automatically format your code and catch style violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pre-commit hooks using tools like Husky to enforce style rules.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Running formatters as part of your CI pipeline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Keeps your codebase clean and consistent without debates over tabs vs. spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-generating-documentation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Generating Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documentation is essential but often neglected. Automation tools can generate and update documentation directly from your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generating API docs with tools like Swagger/OpenAPI or Sphinx.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating diagrams from code using PlantUML or Mermaid.js.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auto-generating changelogs from commit messages using tools like conventional-changelog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Keeps documentation up to date without extra effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-managing-dependencies&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Managing Dependencies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping dependencies up to date manually can be tedious and error-prone. Tools like Dependabot, Renovate, or poetry lock files make this process seamless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Detecting outdated dependencies and submitting pull requests with updates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checking for security vulnerabilities in dependencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ensures your project is secure and avoids technical debt from outdated libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-handling-code-reviews&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Handling Code Reviews&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code reviews are vital but time-consuming. Tools like Reviewable or Gerrit can streamline the process, while automation can handle the mundane parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enforcing code review rules (e.g., required approvals).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automatically assigning reviewers based on the area of code affected.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rejecting commits that don’t meet specific criteria (e.g., failing tests).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Focuses reviewer time on logic and architecture, not style or formatting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-generating-mock-data&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Generating Mock Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manually creating mock data for testing can slow you down. Tools like Faker library (JavaScript, Java, Python), generators in CodeMenu macOS app and Mockaroo website (can also create a fake API when you haven’t created a backend yet) can handle this. You can also use AI like ChatGPT or Claude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generating large datasets for load testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating realistic mock data for testing APIs or UI components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Speeds up testing and helps simulate real-world conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-monitoring-application-performance&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Monitoring Application Performance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manually monitoring app performance and server health is inefficient. Tools like Prometheus, Grafana, and New Relic automate performance tracking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting up alerts for anomalies like high memory usage or slow response times.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Logging key metrics and generating automated reports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Proactively catches issues before users are affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-handling-repetitive-file-or-data-operations&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Handling Repetitive File or Data Operations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tasks like renaming files, transforming datasets, or migrating data can be automated using scripts or tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Batch-renaming files with a script.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data transformations using Python, Pandas, or command-line tools like awk.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exporting/importing databases with automated backup scripts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eliminates repetitive tasks and reduces human error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;9-generating-boilerplate-code&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Generating Boilerplate Code&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a new project or feature often involves writing boilerplate code. Tools like Yeoman, Plop, or cookiecutter can automate this process. You can use a snippets manager like Pieces, Snippety or CodeMenu to store and access them easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generating project scaffolding (e.g., React apps, Express APIs).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating template files for new features or components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Saves time and ensures consistency across projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;10-security-audits-and-code-scanning&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Security Audits and Code Scanning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security and code quality should never be an afterthought. Tools like SonarQube, Snyk, or GitHub’s code scanning features can identify issues early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scanning code for vulnerabilities during pull requests.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Running regular security audits on dependencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It’s Useful:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Prevents vulnerabilities from slipping into production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-started-with-automation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting Started with Automation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin automating, start small. Identify repetitive tasks that slow you down and explore tools that can handle them. Use scripting languages like Python, Bash, or PowerShell for custom tasks, and integrate specialized tools into your workflow. Use AI to write scripts and speed up this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/the-power-of-automation-useful-tools-for-automating</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/the-power-of-automation-useful-tools-for-automating</guid>
        
        <category>guide</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Ultimate Guide to Snippet Management with CodeMenu</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;In the fast-paced world of software development, efficiency isn’t just nice to have; it’s essential. Code snippets, those handy pieces of reusable code, can significantly boost your productivity, but only if you manage them effectively. Enter &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/codemenu.html&quot;&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/a&gt; by Extiri, a snippet manager designed not just for storing code but for transforming how you code, design, and even think about your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s your ultimate guide to leveraging CodeMenu for an unparalleled coding workflow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-centralize-your-codebase&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Centralize Your Codebase&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to revolutionizing your workflow is centralization. CodeMenu allows you to store snippets in over 55 programming languages, from Python to TypeScript, ensuring that no matter what project you’re working on, your go-to solutions are just a click away. Instead of rummaging through old projects or scattered notes, you have everything organized in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action: Begin by migrating all your existing snippets into CodeMenu, using tags or groups to categorize by project or function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-instant-access-with-snippet-suggestions&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Instant Access with Snippet Suggestions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speed is of the essence in development. CodeMenu’s Suggestions app integrates directly into your code editor, allowing you to summon snippets with abbreviations or even natural language queries. This means less time searching, more time coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action: Set up your most used snippets with abbreviations or explore the AI-driven search to find snippets by describing what you need in plain English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-ai-driven-enhancements&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. AI-Driven Enhancements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CodeMenu isn’t just about storage; it’s about smart assistance. Use AI features for natural language searches, screenshot-to-text conversion, or even generating titles and descriptions for your snippets. These functionalities run offline, ensuring your privacy while keeping your workflow fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action: Try taking a screenshot of code in a programming tutorial to turn it into text or use the AI to generate a description for a complex snippet you just created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-adapt-and-enhance-with-placeholders-and-latex&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Adapt and Enhance with Placeholders and LaTeX&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One size doesn’t fit all in coding. CodeMenu’s use of placeholders allows you to make snippets adaptable to different contexts. Add LaTeX for mathematical or algorithmic explanations, enhancing your snippets’ utility for documentation or teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action: Create a template snippet for a common function with placeholders for variable names or values, making it instantly reusable across different projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-test-and-run-within-codemenu&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Test and Run Within CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers often need to test snippets before integrating them into larger projects. CodeMenu provides an environment to test JavaScript snippets directly, with the option to add support for other languages. This immediate feedback loop can save hours of back-and-forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action: Start testing your snippets within CodeMenu before committing them to your project, ensuring they work as intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-expand-your-toolkit-with-utilities&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Expand Your Toolkit with Utilities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CodeMenu isn’t just about code. It’s packed with utilities like code image generation, mockup data generation (like UUID, emails, etc), text encoding/decoding, RegEx testing, code translation, and number system conversion. These tools can be lifesavers in a variety of scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action: Use these utilities to streamline tasks outside of direct coding, like generating test data or understanding how a piece of code might look visually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-customization-and-integration&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Customization and Integration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every developer’s workflow is unique. CodeMenu allows for customization through layouts, code themes, shortcuts, HTTP server capabilities for integration, and even custom scripts called automations. This flexibility means CodeMenu can grow with you, adapting to new tools or methods you adopt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action: Customize CodeMenu to integrate with your favorite tools, write an automation modifying snippets or create shortcuts that match your muscle memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By integrating CodeMenu into your daily coding routine, you’re not just managing snippets; you’re enhancing your entire development process. From centralizing your knowledge base to leveraging AI for smarter work, CodeMenu is more than a tool; it’s a partner in your coding journey. Start today, and watch how your productivity and creativity soar.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/ultimate-guide-to-snippet-management-with-codemenu</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/blog/posts/ultimate-guide-to-snippet-management-with-codemenu</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>guide</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
