<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Extiri Blog</title>
    <description>blog about Extiri, programming and cybersecurity
</description>
    <link>https://extiri.com/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://extiri.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:49:41 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:49:41 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>CodeMenu as a File System for Your AI Agents</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the evolving world of AI development, there’s a growing buzz around “filesystems for AI”—essentially, structured ways to organize and access data that empower AI agents to work more intelligently and autonomously. Think of it as giving your AI a well-organized filing cabinet where it can pull out exactly what it needs without rummaging through chaos. This trend is picking up steam because AI agents aren’t just chatbots anymore; they’re becoming active participants in coding, research, and problem-solving workflows. They need reliable, queryable repositories to fetch context, code patterns, or prompts on demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter CodeMenu, a nifty Mac app from Extiri that’s quietly positioning itself as a perfect fit for this niche. It’s not marketed as a filesystem per se, but its design as an offline-first knowledge base for developers makes it an ideal local “file system” for AI agents. I’ve been exploring it, and it’s got that warm, practical feel—like a trusted notebook that’s always at your side. Let me walk you through what it offers, why it aligns with this trend, and some real-world use cases that might inspire you to give it a spin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-makes-codemenu-a-file-system-for-ai&quot;&gt;What Makes CodeMenu a “File System” for AI?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core, CodeMenu is a developer-focused tool for storing and managing code snippets, AI prompts, notes, images, and more. Everything lives locally on your Mac in a Realm database, which means no cloud dependencies, no subscriptions, and full privacy—your data stays put unless you choose otherwise. This offline-first approach is a breath of fresh air in a world of always-online tools, and it echoes the reliability we expect from a traditional file system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s where it shines for AI: CodeMenu isn’t just a static storage bin. It structures your data in a way that’s easy for humans &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; machines to navigate. You can organize artifacts into “Spaces” for project isolation, “Stashes” for quick ideas, and use tags, groups, and even a visual knowledge graph to link things together. Imagine a file system where files aren’t isolated silos—they’re connected nodes in a graph, allowing for relational queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real magic for AI agents comes from its integration points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MCP Server&lt;/strong&gt;: This lets AI tools like Claude Desktop or Cursor directly query your CodeMenu library. Your agent can say something like “CodeMenu fetch the ‘stripe-webhook’ snippet” and pull in verified code without you copying and pasting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTTP Server&lt;/strong&gt;: Running locally (e.g., via curl to localhost), it exposes your snippets as an API. This turns CodeMenu into a programmable data source that AI scripts or agents can tap into programmatically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CLI Tool (cdmn)&lt;/strong&gt;: A terminal interface with fuzzy search and JSON output, perfect for scripting AI workflows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like having a lightweight, developer-centric database that AI can read from, much like how modern AI systems use vector databases or file systems for long-term memory. And with support for over 60 languages, syntax highlighting, and rendering for Markdown, LaTeX, images, and even regex testing, it’s robust enough to handle diverse AI needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;real-use-cases-bringing-it-to-life&quot;&gt;Real Use Cases: Bringing It to Life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this concrete, let’s look at some practical scenarios where CodeMenu acts as that essential filesystem layer for AI agents. These are drawn from how developers are already using it, adapted to highlight the AI angle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building Smarter Coding Assistants&lt;/strong&gt;: Suppose you’re working on a web app with Stripe integration. You’ve stored webhook handlers, error-handling patterns, and test prompts in CodeMenu, tagged and linked in a knowledge graph. Now, integrate it with an AI agent in Cursor (an AI-powered code editor). The agent queries CodeMenu via the MCP Server to retrieve a “stripe-webhook” snippet, then generates unit tests or refactors code based on that context. No more losing track of your best practices—your AI pulls from a structured “file” of proven code, reducing hallucinations and improving output quality. CodeMenu can also store your Agent Skills and AGENTS.md giving you a centralized place to manage them. I’ve seen devs save hours this way, turning scattered notes into a reliable AI memory bank.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automating Research Workflows&lt;/strong&gt;: For AI agents handling research or OSINT (open-source intelligence), CodeMenu can store screenshots, notes, links, and prompts as interconnected artifacts. Picture an agent tasked with analyzing design trends: It fetches a group of design tokens (colors, refs) from CodeMenu’s API, cross-references them with stored images, and generates a report. It’s neutral and warm in practice: No over-reliance on external APIs, just local, organized data that keeps your agent grounded and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scripting Bulk Operations for AI Pipelines&lt;/strong&gt;: CodeMenu’s JavaScript scripting lets you automate tasks, but pair it with AI for more power. Say you’re maintaining a library of AI prompts for generating documentation. An AI agent uses the HTTP server to list all prompts tagged “docs-gen,” then scripts a bulk update (e.g., adding ethical guidelines to each). This filesystem-like access means your AI can “read” and “write” to the repo programmatically, evolving it over time. A real win for solo devs or small teams building custom AI tools—it’s like giving your agent write access to a shared drive, but safer and more structured.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offline AI Experimentation&lt;/strong&gt;: In areas with spotty internet (or just for privacy), CodeMenu’s local setup is gold. Store system prompts, templates, and code for fine-tuning small models. An AI agent running locally (via tools like Ollama) queries CodeMenu for prompt patterns, tests them offline, and iterates. This use case feels particularly human-centered—it’s about empowering you to tinker without barriers, aligning with the trend of democratizing AI through accessible “filesystems.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-this-matters-in-the-bigger-picture&quot;&gt;Why This Matters in the Bigger Picture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As AI agents become more agentic—handling tasks end-to-end—they’ll need better ways to manage knowledge. Traditional filesystems are too rigid, cloud services too invasive, but tools like CodeMenu bridge the gap with a developer-friendly, AI-ready structure. It’s not perfect for every setup (it’s Mac-only for now), but its free model and extensibility make it approachable for anyone dipping into this trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious about enhancing your AI workflows, I’d gently suggest downloading CodeMenu and experimenting. Start small: Populate a Space with your go-to snippets, fire up the MCP Server, and see how your favorite AI tool interacts with it. It’s a subtle shift, but one that could make your agents feel less like tools and more like thoughtful collaborators. What do you think—ready to organize your AI’s “files”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try &lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt; free for 7 days → &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/codemenu-snippet-manager/id1583463781?mt=12&quot;&gt;Mac App Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/codemenu-as-a-filesystem-ai-agent</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/codemenu-as-a-filesystem-ai-agent</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>codemenu</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why 2026 Is the Year of Local-First Productivity Tools (and How CodeMenu Fits In)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re copying API keys into ChatGPT prompts, uploading proprietary code to cloud snippet managers, and syncing our entire knowledge bases through servers we don’t control. Somewhere along the way, we normalized sending our most valuable work artifacts through someone else’s infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s changing in 2026 — and it’s about time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;privacy-isnt-optional-anymore&quot;&gt;Privacy Isn’t Optional Anymore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tools we used to trust are now the ones we question. Every snippet, every piece of code, every design decision we document potentially flows through a third-party server. With data breaches making headlines weekly and companies quietly training AI models on user content, developers are waking up to an uncomfortable truth: cloud-first isn’t always the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem isn’t cloud sync itself—it’s the assumption that it must be the default. Your code snippets, your AI prompts, your research notes—these don’t need to live on someone else’s computer. They shouldn’t have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local-first tools flip this model. Your data stays on your machine. You choose when (and if) to sync. You control who sees what. And when you close your laptop on a plane, everything still works because it was never dependent on someone else’s servers in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ai-needs-context-not-your-companys-secrets&quot;&gt;AI Needs Context, Not Your Company’s Secrets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AI productivity revolution came with a catch: to be useful, AI needs context. The more it knows about your codebase, your patterns, your preferences, the better it performs. But feeding that context into cloud APIs means broadcasting your intellectual property to external services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates a painful choice: accept reduced productivity by keeping AI out of your workflow, or accept privacy risks by sending everything to the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On-device AI changes the equation entirely. You get intelligent assistance—semantic search, content generation, automated tagging—without any data leaving your machine. The AI model runs locally, learns from your patterns privately, and helps you work faster without compromising what matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;codemenu-your-private-knowledge-system&quot;&gt;CodeMenu: Your Private Knowledge System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where CodeMenu comes in. It’s built from the ground up as a local-first tool that treats your privacy as a feature, not an afterthought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything you save—code snippets in 60+ languages, design references, color palettes, AI prompts, screenshots—lives on your Mac. The on-device AI features (generation, chat, semantic search) run entirely on your hardware. Nothing gets sent to external servers unless you explicitly choose to sync or share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes this powerful isn’t just the privacy angle. It’s the workflow. With parameterized templates, you can create living boilerplates that adapt to different contexts. The JavaScript automation and HTTP API let you build custom workflows that connect CodeMenu to your other tools. Built-in utilities (RegEx tester, converters, mock data generators) mean fewer context switches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because it’s offline-first, everything works on planes, in basements, or when your internet inevitably decides to fail right before a demo. Your augmented memory is always available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For teams that do need sharing, CodeMenu’s optional sync and Snippets Store provide controlled collaboration—you decide what to share, when to share it, and who sees it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clipguru-local-first-for-your-mobile-workflow&quot;&gt;ClipGuru: Local-First for Your Mobile Workflow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everything needs the power of a full snippet manager. Sometimes you just need to capture a URL from Safari, save a quote you’ll reference later, or keep a piece of code accessible across your iPhone and Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru takes the local-first philosophy and distills it into a lightweight clipboard manager for iOS, iPadOS, and macOS. Text, links, and images sync via iCloud (which means your data stays in Apple’s ecosystem, not a third-party server), and the custom keyboard extension gives you instant access without app switching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s intentionally simple—no overwhelming features, no complex setup, just fast capture and smart search. The free version saves 4 clips, and Pro unlocks unlimited history and tags for about the price of a coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of it as CodeMenu’s mobile companion: ClipGuru handles quick captures and clipboard management across devices, while CodeMenu serves as your deeper knowledge system on Mac. Together, they create a local-first workflow that scales from quick mobile snippets to comprehensive knowledge management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-offline-first-future-is-already-here&quot;&gt;The Offline-First Future Is Already Here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re seeing a shift away from the “everything must be cloud-based” mentality of the 2010s. Developers are choosing tools that respect their privacy, work offline, and give them control over their data. The technology is mature—local AI models are powerful, device storage is cheap, and sync protocols exist that don’t require surrendering your data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2026 won’t be the year everyone abandons cloud tools. But it will be the year local-first becomes a serious consideration rather than a niche preference. When you can have the best of both worlds—powerful features and complete privacy—why would you settle for less?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your code, your snippets, your knowledge base—these are your intellectual property. They deserve to live somewhere you control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ready to go local-first?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try &lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt; free for 7 days → &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/codemenu-snippet-manager/id1583463781?mt=12&quot;&gt;Mac App Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or grab &lt;strong&gt;ClipGuru&lt;/strong&gt; for quick clipboard access → &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/pl/app/clipguru/id6753787446&quot;&gt;App Store (iOS, iPadOS, macOS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/the-year-of-local-software</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/the-year-of-local-software</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Use Code Snippets on Your Mac</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;You found a piece of code online-maybe in Python, Bash, JavaScript, Ruby, or even C-and you’re wondering how to actually run it on your Mac.&lt;br /&gt;
You’re in the right place. I’ll walk you through how to run snippets in both interpreted &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; compiled languages, explain what’s happening behind the scenes, and keep it simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-going-on-interpreted-vs-compiled-languages&quot;&gt;What’s going on: interpreted vs compiled languages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into examples, here’s a quick overview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interpreted languages&lt;/strong&gt; (like Python, Bash scripts, JavaScript via Node.js, Ruby) are executed by a program (an interpreter) line by line. You paste code and it runs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiled languages&lt;/strong&gt; (such as C, C++ and others) require a &lt;em&gt;compiler&lt;/em&gt;. The compiler transforms your source code into a binary executable that your Mac can run directly. That means a few extra steps: install the compiler → compile the code → run the executable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does this matter to you? Because when you pick up a snippet, you’ll want to know whether you can paste it and run it immediately (interpreted), or if you need a toolchain set up (compiled).&lt;br /&gt;
Let’s go through both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;option-1-running-interpreted-languages&quot;&gt;Option 1: Running Interpreted Languages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;python&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check if Python is installed:
    &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;  python3 --version
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see something like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Python 3.9.x&lt;/code&gt;, you’re ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run code interactively:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;python3
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Now you’re at the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; prompt. Paste:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello from Python!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Press Enter → you’ll see the output. To exit, type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;exit()&lt;/code&gt; or press &lt;strong&gt;Ctrl + D&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run a script from a file:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Open a text editor, paste your snippet.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Save it as &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;myscript.py&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In Terminal, navigate to its folder.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/Desktop     &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# adjust path as needed&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Run:&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;python3 myscript.py
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bash--shell&quot;&gt;Bash / Shell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the snippet looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello from the shell!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can simply paste it into Terminal and hit Enter-done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a multi-line script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;nano myscript.sh         &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# open a simple editor&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# paste code&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# save with Ctrl + O, enter; exit with Ctrl + X&lt;/span&gt;
chmod +x myscript.sh     &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# make it executable&lt;/span&gt;
./myscript.sh            &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# run it&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;javascript-with-nodejs&quot;&gt;JavaScript with Node.js&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use JavaScript outside of a browser you’ll generally install &lt;strong&gt;Node.js&lt;/strong&gt;. I’ll cover installation in the next section. Once installed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interactive mode:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;node
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;You’ll see a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; prompt. Then:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-js highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello from Node.js!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Press Enter → output appears. Exit with Ctrl + C.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running from file:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;nano app.js           &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# create/edit file&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# paste:&lt;/span&gt;
console.log&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;This runs using Node.js&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# save &amp;amp; exit&lt;/span&gt;
node app.js
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;Ruby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;ruby -v
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then create a file &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script.rb&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-ruby highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello from Ruby!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save, then run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;ruby script.rb
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-nodejs-so-you-can-run-js&quot;&gt;Installing Node.js (so you can run JS)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to get Node.js running on your Mac:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit the official Node.js site and download the &lt;strong&gt;LTS&lt;/strong&gt; version (https://nodejs.org).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open the downloaded &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pkg&lt;/code&gt; installer and follow the on-screen steps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After installation, open Terminal and type:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;  node -v
  npm -v
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see version numbers, indicating successful installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optionally, you can use the Homebrew package manager:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;brew update
brew install node
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then verify as before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;option-2-running-compiled-languages---example-with-c&quot;&gt;Option 2: Running Compiled Languages - Example with C&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using compiled languages means one extra step: building (compiling) the code before you run it. Let’s walk through C on Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;installing-the-compiler&quot;&gt;Installing the compiler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Mac can use Apple’s built-in toolchain (Clang) or you can install GNU GCC. Here’s how to set up the basic tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;xcode-select --install
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This installs Apple’s Command Line Tools (which include Clang) without needing the full Xcode app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you prefer GNU GCC:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;brew install gcc
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;And verify:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;gcc --version
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;(verify the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gcc&lt;/code&gt; output shows a version string)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;write-a-simple-c-snippet&quot;&gt;Write a simple C snippet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a file named &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hello.c&lt;/code&gt; with content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-c highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;printf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello, C world!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;compile--run&quot;&gt;Compile &amp;amp; Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Terminal, navigate to the folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; /path/to/folder
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then compile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;clang hello.c -o hello
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or if using GCC:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;gcc-13 hello.c -o hello
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;./hello
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;Hello, C world!
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-vs-code-for-c-optional&quot;&gt;Using VS Code for C (optional)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install VS Code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install the C/C++ extension&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hello.c&lt;/code&gt;, then use the built-in terminal (Ctrl + ~) to compile and run as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-quick-peek-at-other-languages-you-might-encounter&quot;&gt;A Quick Peek at Other Languages You Might Encounter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C++&lt;/strong&gt; - Very similar to C; you’ll use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;clang++&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;g++&lt;/code&gt; to compile.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Go&lt;/strong&gt; - Install via &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;brew install go&lt;/code&gt; or official site; run a file with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;go run file.go&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rust&lt;/strong&gt; - Install using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rustup&lt;/code&gt;, compile with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cargo build&lt;/code&gt;, run with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cargo run&lt;/code&gt;.
The pattern stays: install toolchain → compile/build (if needed) → run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;option-3-run--manage-snippets-effortlessly-with-codemenu&quot;&gt;Option 3: Run &amp;amp; Manage Snippets Effortlessly with CodeMenu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re testing a variety of snippets across languages, switching between terminals, editors and computing steps can get tedious. That’s why I built &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/codemenu.html&quot;&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With CodeMenu you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Save and organize snippets (Python, Bash, Ruby, JavaScript, C, and more).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run them instantly without manually opening Terminal each time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep everything in one place so you don’t lose track of “one that worked” or “the version I saved”.
Treat it as a snippet sandbox + launcher-it simplifies your workflow so you can focus on experiments instead of setup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👉 Try it here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/codemenu.html&quot;&gt;CodeMenu for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr-summary&quot;&gt;TL;DR (summary)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interpreted languages (Python, Bash, JS, Ruby) = paste &amp;amp; run almost immediately.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compiled languages (C, C++, Go, etc.) = install compiler → compile → run the executable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On Mac you’ll often use Terminal to run commands; editors like VS Code add comfort.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re working with lots of snippets or switching languages, CodeMenu gives you structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a “developer” to try running code. You just need curiosity and a few practical steps. Start with a simple snippet, run it, see what happens, tweak it. The “typing commands” part might look intimidating-but once you’ve done it once, it becomes second nature.
And when you want to keep your snippets organized, manageable, and easy to run-CodeMenu is there to make life simpler.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/how-to-run-code-snippets-mac</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/how-to-run-code-snippets-mac</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>codemenu-guide</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Study Faster with Read-Aloud PDF Apps</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;Studying isn’t just about logging hours - it’s about how effectively you absorb and retain information. Yet, reading through stacks of PDF textbooks, research papers, and study guides can be time-consuming, mentally draining, and difficult to maintain consistently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where &lt;strong&gt;text-to-speech (TTS) apps&lt;/strong&gt; transform your workflow. By converting written content into natural-sounding audio, they let you &lt;strong&gt;listen to PDFs and other study materials while commuting, exercising, or during your evening routine&lt;/strong&gt;. With the right approach, read-aloud technology can turn otherwise wasted time into productive study sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this guide, you’ll discover:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How listening to PDFs supports faster learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why offline, privacy-focused tools matter for students&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practical strategies to integrate read-aloud PDFs into your study routine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How &lt;strong&gt;Chitneek&lt;/strong&gt; helps you study from PDFs anywhere, without internet or privacy concerns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-listening-to-your-study-materials-actually-works&quot;&gt;Why listening to your study materials actually works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional reading requires sustained visual focus, which leads to eye strain and makes it harder to study in non-ideal environments. Listening changes this dynamic completely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study anywhere:&lt;/strong&gt; Convert PDFs to audio and review material while walking to class, cooking dinner, or cleaning your room&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better retention:&lt;/strong&gt; Research shows TTS improves comprehension by engaging multisensory learning - combining visual and auditory processing helps information stick&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible pacing:&lt;/strong&gt; Speed up playback to 1.5x or 2x when reviewing familiar material, or slow down for complex concepts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessibility advantage:&lt;/strong&gt; For students with dyslexia, visual impairments, or reading challenges, TTS removes barriers that make dense PDFs inaccessible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A meta-analysis found that text-to-speech tools showed a meaningful positive effect on reading comprehension for students with reading difficulties, demonstrating this isn’t just a convenience feature - it’s a proven learning tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-formats-you-can-turn-into-audio&quot;&gt;What formats you can turn into audio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PDFs are everywhere in academic life - textbooks, journal articles, lecture slides, assignment briefs. A good TTS app should handle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PDF documents&lt;/strong&gt; – your primary study material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web articles&lt;/strong&gt; – supplementary reading and research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPUB files&lt;/strong&gt; – digital textbooks and study guides&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plain text&lt;/strong&gt; – notes and pasted content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more formats your app supports, the less time you spend converting files or switching between different tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-privacy-matters-cloud-vs-offline-tts&quot;&gt;Why privacy matters: cloud vs. offline TTS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most mainstream TTS apps upload your documents to cloud servers for processing. This raises real concerns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your academic PDFs, research notes, and personal study materials pass through third-party servers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You need constant internet access to use the app&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your reading habits and document content may be tracked or analyzed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slow connections interrupt your study flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offline TTS apps keep everything local.&lt;/strong&gt; Your PDFs never leave your device, you can study anywhere regardless of connectivity, and there’s zero tracking of what you read or when.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For students working with sensitive research, unpublished papers, or simply valuing privacy, offline processing isn’t just a feature - it’s essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meet-chitneek-a-pdf-reader-built-for-learning&quot;&gt;Meet Chitneek: a PDF reader built for learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/chitneek.html&quot;&gt;Chitneek&lt;/a&gt; is designed specifically for students who want to &lt;strong&gt;read aloud PDF files efficiently and privately&lt;/strong&gt;. Unlike cloud-based alternatives, Chitneek processes everything on your device using iOS’s built-in voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why students choose Chitneek:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;True offline functionality:&lt;/strong&gt; Read aloud PDF files with zero internet requirement once saved - perfect for commutes, flights, or anywhere connectivity is limited&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy-first design:&lt;/strong&gt; Files are processed on-device, so your PDFs and reading habits stay completely private&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Natural iOS voices:&lt;/strong&gt; Uses Apple’s built-in voices for clear, consistent narration that sounds natural&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjustable playback:&lt;/strong&gt; Control speech rate and pitch to match your comprehension needs - slow down for difficult research papers, speed up for review&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background listening:&lt;/strong&gt; Keep audio playing while you use other apps, take notes, or browse references&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smart bookmarks:&lt;/strong&gt; Mark important sections to replay difficult material or jump straight to key passages during review&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Format flexibility:&lt;/strong&gt; Import PDFs and EPUBs from Files, share from other apps, paste text, or save web pages to PDF&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stay organized:&lt;/strong&gt; Use named groups to keep your study materials tidy and easy to find&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built-in discovery:&lt;/strong&gt; Find free books from Project Gutenberg and follow RSS feeds directly in the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re working through a 50-page research paper or reviewing lecture notes before an exam, Chitneek lets you study on your terms. A 7-day free trial is available to test both monthly and yearly subscription plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-actually-study-faster-with-read-aloud-pdfs&quot;&gt;How to actually study faster with read-aloud PDFs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just play audio passively. Here’s how to actually learn faster:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pre-read-then-listen&quot;&gt;Pre-read, then listen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skim the PDF first to understand structure and main arguments. Then listen to reinforce and fill gaps in understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-bookmarks-for-key-sections&quot;&gt;Use bookmarks for key sections&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark important passages with Chitneek’s bookmark feature. When reviewing for exams, you can jump straight to the most critical material without scrubbing through audio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;organize-with-named-groups&quot;&gt;Organize with named groups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separate content by subject, priority, or exam date using named groups. This makes finding specific material effortless during review sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;practice-active-recall-while-listening&quot;&gt;Practice active recall while listening&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pause the audio regularly. Summarize what you just heard out loud or write a quick note. This forces your brain to process, not just passively consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;layer-your-learning&quot;&gt;Layer your learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to PDFs during commutes or exercise. Later, sit down and review the same material visually, adding annotations or creating study notes. This dual-mode approach strengthens memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adjust-speed-strategically&quot;&gt;Adjust speed strategically&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First pass on new material: Normal or slightly slower speed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review sessions: 1.5x speed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final pre-exam cramming: 2x speed for familiar content only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Combine with traditional study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Read-aloud PDFs work best as part of a complete study system. Use them for initial exposure and review, but still engage visually with complex diagrams, equations, or tables that don’t convert well to audio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-tts-cant-do-and-what-to-do-instead&quot;&gt;What TTS can’t do (and what to do instead)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be realistic about limitations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex layouts suffer:&lt;/strong&gt; Tables, mathematical equations, and multi-column formats often read awkwardly. You’ll need to review these sections visually in the original PDF.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagrams and images:&lt;/strong&gt; TTS can’t describe figures. Keep the PDF open to glance at visual elements when referenced.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organization matters:&lt;/strong&gt; Without using groups or clear naming, finding specific content later becomes frustrating. Spend a few minutes organizing files upfront.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution:&lt;/strong&gt; Use TTS for prose-heavy content (textbook chapters, research papers, articles). Study graphs, charts, and equations separately with traditional reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ready-to-turn-your-pdfs-into-audio&quot;&gt;Ready to turn your PDFs into audio?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text-to-speech apps transform how efficiently you can study by &lt;strong&gt;turning idle time into productive learning time&lt;/strong&gt;. By listening to read-aloud PDFs during your daily routine, you can cover more material, reinforce retention, and maintain momentum even when sitting down to read isn’t practical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a tool that reads PDFs aloud without compromising your privacy, &lt;strong&gt;Chitneek&lt;/strong&gt; delivers on-device processing, natural iOS voices, and the flexibility students need. No cloud uploads, no tracking, no accounts required - just your PDFs converted to audio, ready whenever you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start studying smarter by making every moment count. Try Chitneek’s 7-day free trial and experience what it’s like to have your entire PDF library accessible as audio, anywhere you go. Learn more &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/chitneek.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/pl/app/chitneek-read-aloud/id6749827870&quot;&gt;download now&lt;/a&gt; from the App Store on iOS.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/how-to-study-read-aloud-pdf</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/how-to-study-read-aloud-pdf</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>study-guide</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Guide to CodeMenu: How to add a programming language for running?</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;CodeMenu is a handy snippet manager for macOS - and one of its neat features is the ability to run snippets. Out of the box it runs JavaScript, but it’s flexible: you can teach CodeMenu to run almost any language by pointing it at the right command-line utility or script. This short guide shows two simple examples (Python and C) so you can add languages quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-codemenu-runs-snippets&quot;&gt;How CodeMenu runs snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CodeMenu executes snippets by writing the snippet to a temporary file and invoking the language runner you configured for that language. The runner can be a simple interpreter (for languages like Python or Ruby) or a small shell script that compiles and executes code (for C, C++, etc.). The snippet’s stdout is captured and shown as the snippet output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because CodeMenu runs user-specified binaries from a restricted location, you have to link the utilities you want to allow into CodeMenu’s utilities directory - this keeps execution safe and discoverable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-1---add-python-using-python3&quot;&gt;Example 1 - Add Python (using python3)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you already have &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python3&lt;/code&gt; installed, adding it is straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open a terminal and change to CodeMenu’s application scripts directory:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/Library/Application&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\ &lt;/span&gt;Scripts/id.thedev.marcin.CodeMenu
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a symbolic link to the interpreter (this makes the binary visible to CodeMenu):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;ln -s &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;which python3&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; .
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can replace &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$(which python3)&lt;/code&gt; with an absolute path if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/cdmn-guide/link-utility.png&quot; alt=&quot;Linking python3 to CodeMenu utilities&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open CodeMenu → Preferences → Code execution. Click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;+ Add&lt;/code&gt;, choose a Language (e.g. Python) and set the Language runner to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python3&lt;/code&gt; (it will show the name of the file you linked). Save the language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/cdmn-guide/code-execution-settings-tab.png&quot; alt=&quot;Code execution settings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now a snippet saved with the Python language will be written to a temp file and executed with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python3 temp_file.py&lt;/code&gt;, and its output will be captured by CodeMenu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-2---add-c-using-clang&quot;&gt;Example 2 - Add C (using clang)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compiled languages usually need a tiny wrapper to compile and run the temporary file. You can add such a wrapper as a runner script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Return to the utilities directory:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/Library/Application&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\ &lt;/span&gt;Scripts/id.thedev.marcin.CodeMenu
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a runner script (example &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;clang_run.sh&lt;/code&gt;) with the following contents:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/zsh&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# $1 is the path to the temporary source file provided by CodeMenu&lt;/span&gt;
clang -o /var/tmp/compiled_app &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
chmod +x /var/tmp/compiled_app
/var/tmp/compiled_app
rm /var/tmp/compiled_app
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This script compiles the temporary source file to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/var/tmp/compiled_app&lt;/code&gt;, runs it, then removes the binary. Adjust the paths or flags if you need additional options (e.g. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-O2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-Wall&lt;/code&gt;, or linking libraries).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the script executable:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;chmod +x clang_run.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In CodeMenu → Preferences → Code execution, add a new language entry, select the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;clang_run.sh&lt;/code&gt; script as the Language runner, and name the language (e.g. C). Save.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now when you run a C snippet, CodeMenu will call your script and capture the program output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tips and safety notes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep runners in the special application scripts directory so CodeMenu can control what executes. Don’t symlink random user binaries from untrusted locations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For interpreted languages, prefer pointing to an interpreter (python3, ruby, node) that reads the temp file and prints result to stdout.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For compiled languages, write a small wrapper script that compiles to a temp location and runs the binary; make sure to clean up temporary files.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a runner needs extra libraries or environment variables, either embed them in the script or use a wrapper that sets those values before invoking the compiler/interpreter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it - with these steps you can add new languages to CodeMenu and run snippets right from the app. If you’d like, I can add examples for other languages (Node, Ruby, Swift) or draft a small, shareable runner script template you can drop into the utilities folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading - enjoy running code with CodeMenu!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/codemenu-guide-add-programming-language</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/codemenu-guide-add-programming-language</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>codemenu-guide</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ranking of The Best Snippet Managers for Mac 2025</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;As developers, we all face the same problem: brilliant ideas scattered across chat logs, forgotten code experiments buried in old projects, and that perfect solution you swear you wrote last month but can’t find anywhere. Your code snippets deserve better than living in chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mac ecosystem offers several solid snippet managers, each with its own philosophy. Let’s look at what’s out there and help you find the right fit for your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-contenders&quot;&gt;The Contenders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;codemenu-your-augmented-memory&quot;&gt;CodeMenu: Your Augmented Memory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/codemenu-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;CodeMenu Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CodeMenu is a standout in this space — more than a snippet manager, it’s a local-first personal knowledge system that blends code, visual references, and on-device intelligence into a single, extensible workspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why it matters:&lt;/strong&gt; CodeMenu doesn’t just store snippets; it remembers context. Store color palettes, design notes, AI prompts, screenshots, research, and visual references alongside code. Everything gets rich descriptions with Markdown, LaTeX, images, and diagrams, and on-device AI (generation, chat, semantic search) helps you find and adapt content without sending data off your machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it shines:&lt;/strong&gt; With parameterized templates, JavaScript automation, an HTTP API, and built-in utilities (converters, mock data, RegEx tester), CodeMenu reduces context switching and scales from a single-user sandbox to team workflows via optional sync and the Snippets Store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Professionals who want a single, private, and extensible place for code, design, and research — a tool that helps you remember, adapt, and ship faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snippetslab-the-traditional-choice&quot;&gt;SnippetsLab: The Traditional Choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.renfei.org/snippets-lab/images/Landing/hero2.webp&quot; alt=&quot;SnippetsLab Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SnippetsLab has been around since 2015 and became completely free in November 2024. It’s a polished, Mac-native snippet manager that does one thing well: organizing code snippets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; The interface is clean and developer-focused. With support for over 580 languages, multi-level folders, tags, and smart groups, it offers solid organizational tools. The menubar assistant gives you quick access without opening the main window, and iCloud sync works reliably across Macs. The Markdown support is comprehensive, including Mermaid diagrams and LaTeX formulas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; SnippetsLab is strictly a snippet organizer - nothing more. There’s no iOS version, no AI features, no automation beyond basic organization. If you need parameterized templates or want to inject dynamic data into your snippets, you’ll need to look elsewhere. It’s Mac-only, and while the GitHub Gist integration exists, it’s one-way for exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Developers who want a straightforward, free snippet library without bells and whistles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snippety-the-text-expansion-specialist&quot;&gt;Snippety: The Text Expansion Specialist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://snippety.app/images/app-main-screen-new.png&quot; alt=&quot;Snippety App&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snippety ($24.99 one-time purchase) positions itself as a productivity tool with a focus on text expansion and automation across macOS, iOS, and iPadOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; The snippet expander feature is excellent - type your keyword and your snippet appears instantly without opening the app. It supports 50+ languages with syntax highlighting, nearly 250 themes, and includes 19 smart placeholders for dynamic content like dates, AI-assisted text (via OpenAI API or custom providers), and command-line scripts. The iOS and iPadOS companion app with a custom keyboard is genuinely useful, and iCloud sync keeps everything synchronized across Apple devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; While Snippety excels at text expansion and has AI integration through OpenAI’s API, it’s primarily designed for rapid text insertion rather than building a comprehensive knowledge base. The organizational structure is simpler compared to dedicated snippet managers. It’s also Apple-exclusive - no Windows or Linux support if you work across platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Apple users who want fast text expansion with cross-device access and don’t mind a one-time purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snipperapp-2-the-github-gist-integration-champion&quot;&gt;SnipperApp 2: The GitHub Gist Integration Champion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://snipperapp.com/static/add34ebf75c8b45d46ca17d2d94df70f/337b1/app-v211-light.webp&quot; alt=&quot;SnipperApp 2 Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SnipperApp 2 (free with subscription options) is a native Swift-based snippet manager designed specifically for developers who live in the GitHub ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; Full GitHub Gist integration is the standout feature - sync, edit, and manage your gists directly from the app. With 120+ programming languages supported, the editor includes all the essentials: syntax highlighting, line numbers, invisible character display, and tab size customization. It supports multiple storage options (local, iCloud, GitHub), works offline-first, and includes Markdown preview mode. The ability to share snippets via secret links is handy for quick collaboration. Image attachments, tags, folders with drag-and-drop, and backup/restore functionality round out a solid feature set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s Mac-only with no iOS companion app. The subscription model ($3.99 monthly, $19.99 annual, or $39.99 lifetime) may not appeal to everyone, especially with free alternatives available. While feature-rich for code management, it lacks advanced automation, AI features, or dynamic templates. The interface, while functional, is more utilitarian than modern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Developers heavily invested in GitHub Gist who want a dedicated Mac app for managing their gists with proper organization and offline support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;masscode-the-open-source-alternative&quot;&gt;massCode: The Open-Source Alternative&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://masscode.io/preview.png&quot; alt=&quot;massCode Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;massCode is completely free and open-source, built with Electron, Vue, and CodeMirror for cross-platform compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s free, period. Multi-level folders, tags, and fragments (tabs within snippets) provide decent organization. CodeMirror powers the editor with support for 160+ grammars out of the box (600+ available through .tmLanguage files). The HTML/CSS preview feature is handy for front-end work, Markdown support includes Mermaid diagrams, and there’s even a presentation mode for turning snippets into slideshows. It works on Windows, Linux, and macOS, and being open-source means community contributions drive development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; No built-in sync - you’ll need to manually set up a cloud folder if you want cross-device access. The Electron foundation means it’s heavier on system resources than native apps. While feature-rich, the interface can feel less polished than commercial alternatives. AI features and advanced automation are absent, and being community-driven means feature development can be unpredictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Developers who value open-source software and need cross-platform support without spending money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clipguru-the-lightweight-mobile-first-choice&quot;&gt;ClipGuru: The Lightweight Mobile-First Choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/main-screen-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;ClipGuru Interface&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru is a lightweight clipboard manager that works seamlessly across iOS, iPadOS, and macOS, designed for quick capture and easy retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it gets right:&lt;/strong&gt; The interface is beautifully simple and native to Apple platforms. Save text, links, and images with one tap, and the smart search makes finding anything instant. The custom keyboard extension lets you access your clips from any app without switching contexts - perfect for rapid workflows. The share extension works from Safari and other apps, making it effortless to collect research, quotes, and URLs. With support for Apple Vision Pro and requiring only iOS 17.6+, it’s built for modern Apple devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where it’s limited:&lt;/strong&gt; ClipGuru is intentionally lightweight, which means it lacks advanced features like syntax highlighting for code, dynamic templates, or automation. The free version saves only 4 clips (unlimited with Pro upgrade for ~$1.25). There’s no AI features, no parameterized templates, and no advanced organizational structures beyond tags. It’s Apple ecosystem only - no Windows or Linux support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best for:&lt;/strong&gt; Apple users who want a simple, fast, mobile-friendly clipboard manager that syncs across devices without complexity. Ideal for non-developers or those who prioritize simplicity over power features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feature-comparison&quot;&gt;Feature Comparison&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how these tools stack up across key capabilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Feature&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;ClipGuru&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;SnippetsLab&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Snippety&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;SnipperApp 2&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;massCode&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Syntax Highlighting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;60+ languages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;580+ languages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50+ languages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;120+ languages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;160+ (600+ available)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-Platform&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mac only&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;macOS, iOS, iPadOS, Vision&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mac only&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;macOS, iOS, iPadOS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mac only&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mac, Windows, Linux&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (on-device: generation, chat, search)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (OpenAI/Ollama API)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dynamic Templates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (parameterized)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (19 placeholders)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visual Content&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (images, colors, screenshots)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (images, links)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (images, files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (images)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offline-First&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (fully local)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (optional iCloud)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (optional iCloud)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (iCloud sync)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (offline-first)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (no built-in sync)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text Expansion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (abbreviations)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (menubar)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (primary feature)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built-in Utilities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (editors, converters, RegEx)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (HTML preview, slides)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub Integration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (Gist export)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (full Gist sync)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyboard Extension&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share Extension&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (JS + HTTP server)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (scripts)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (sync + Store)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (iCloud)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (secret links)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Manual sharing&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Markdown + LaTeX&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (+ Mermaid)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (preview)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✓ (+ Mermaid)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pricing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$29.99 one-time / $3.99 monthly (7-day free trial)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free (4 clips) / ~$1.25 Pro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$24.99 one-time&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free / $3.99 monthly / $19.99 annual / $39.99 lifetime&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free (open-source)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pricing for United States (ClipGuru Pro in PLN ≈ $1.25 USD)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bottom-line&quot;&gt;The Bottom Line&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choosing a snippet manager depends on what you actually need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt; if you want an intelligent, extensible personal knowledge system that handles everything from code to design to research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ClipGuru&lt;/strong&gt; if you want a simple, mobile-first clipboard manager that works beautifully across Apple devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SnippetsLab&lt;/strong&gt; if you want a free, focused code snippet organizer with no frills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snippety&lt;/strong&gt; if text expansion speed across Apple devices is your priority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SnipperApp 2&lt;/strong&gt; if you live in GitHub Gists and want native Mac management with offline support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;massCode&lt;/strong&gt; if you need free, open-source, cross-platform compatibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best snippet manager isn’t about feature checklists - it’s about matching your workflow. Traditional snippet managers organize what you’ve saved. ClipGuru keeps your clipboard accessible across devices. SnipperApp bridges your local work with GitHub. CodeMenu becomes the thinking partner that helps you remember, discover, and ship better work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your ideas deserve a home that works as hard as you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ready to try our apps?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ClipGuru&lt;/strong&gt;: Available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/pl/app/clipguru/id6753787446&quot;&gt;App Store&lt;/a&gt; for iOS, iPadOS, and macOS. Free with optional Pro upgrade. Learn more about our &lt;a href=&quot;/clipguru.html&quot;&gt;clipboard manager for iOS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt;: Available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/codemenu-snippet-manager/id1583463781?mt=12&quot;&gt;Mac App Store&lt;/a&gt; with a 7-day free trial, or purchase a one-time license. Learn more about our &lt;a href=&quot;/codemenu.html&quot;&gt;snippet manager for macOS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/the-best-snippet-manager</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/the-best-snippet-manager</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introducing ClipGuru — a lightweight clipboard manager</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;ClipGuru is a small, mobile-first clipboard manager built for iPhone and iPad. It solves a simple problem: when you copy something important on your device, you should be able to save it and find it again. Add clips quickly by tapping Paste inside the app or by typing a new clip — saved items are then easy to search and reuse. The macOS app complements the mobile experience for when you’re on a desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all been there — on your phone or tablet you copy a quick link or quote, then later it’s gone because you copied something else. ClipGuru gives you a simple place to save those items: tap Paste in the app (or enter the content) to add it to your ClipGuru history. Once saved, clips are searchable and ready to reuse across your devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/main-screen-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Main screen&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-is-clipguru-for&quot;&gt;Who is ClipGuru for?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru is for anyone who copies things a lot: writers, developers, designers, students, researchers, and people who simply like to keep small pieces of information handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Researching an article: copy quotes, links, facts, and find them later without opening dozens of tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design work: copy screenshots or small assets to reuse in presentations and mockups.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multi-device workflow: copy on iPad, paste on Mac, continue your work uninterrupted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-makes-clipguru-different&quot;&gt;What makes ClipGuru different?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/keyboard-in-messages-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Keyboard in messages&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lightweight and focused: it does one job well — store and retrieve clipboard items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fast search: find past clips by keyword in seconds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multi-device friendly: saved clips sync across your devices via iCloud — add a clip on your iPhone or iPad and it will appear on your other devices (macOS included) shortly after.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Special keyboard: thanks to a custom keyboard you can access snippets anywhere you need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quick review: review your snippets and decide whether you want to keep or delete them without distractions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;find-snippets-quicker&quot;&gt;Find snippets quicker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/semantic-search-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Semantic search&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever copied five different things in a row and needed the third one? ClipGuru helps you avoid clipboard roulette: paste items into the app as you go, then search by keyword to find them instantly. Results are fast and support simple filters so you can narrow results quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keep-your-favorites-close&quot;&gt;Keep your favorites close&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some clips matter more than others — a signature line, a frequently shared link, or a small image you reuse. Pin those items to keep them at the top of your list so they’re one tap away when you need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lightweight-by-design&quot;&gt;Lightweight by design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru intentionally avoids feature bloat. No complex tagging systems or heavy UIs — just a clean history, favorites, and fast search. It’s designed to help without getting in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;room-to-grow&quot;&gt;Room to grow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/clipguru-screenshots/review-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Review&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial release focuses on the essentials. We’ll add features based on feedback, but the core promise remains: a small, reliable place to save and find the clips you care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru offers a simple, no-fuss approach to clipboard management. If you often copy things and want a reliable way to save and reuse them across devices, ClipGuru is built for that. Try it on your phone or tablet and see how it fits into your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re keeping the initial release simple and iterating based on feedback. If you have ideas or workflows you’d love ClipGuru to support, tell us — we’re listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClipGuru is available on iPhone, iPad, and Mac. Try it and let your clipboard finally work for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, give it a try on your phone or tablet — see how it fits into your mobile workflow and let your clips work for you. ClipGuru stores &lt;strong&gt;text&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;links&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;images&lt;/strong&gt; that you add. Paste into the app (tap Paste) on iPhone or iPad to add a clip; saved clips sync via iCloud and will be available on your other devices, including the macOS companion app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because honestly, we’ve all got better things to do than hunt for that thing we copied five minutes ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-get-started&quot;&gt;Lets get started&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download ClipGuru from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/pl/app/clipguru/id6753787446&quot;&gt;App Store&lt;/a&gt;. The app is mobile-first (iPhone and iPad) but it’s also available on macOS. Learn more &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/clipguru.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/introducing-clipguru</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/introducing-clipguru</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Best Dev Habits to Save Time Every Day: Using Boilerplate, Snippets, and Templates</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a common misconception that productive developers are the ones who type the fastest or memorize the most syntax. In reality, the developers who consistently ship quality work and never seem stressed aren’t necessarily working harder—they’re working smarter by eliminating friction from their daily routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about your own workflow for a second. How much time do you spend recreating the same boilerplate? Looking up commands you’ve run a thousand times? Switching between your editor, browser tabs, and terminal just to find that one piece of documentation? These tiny interruptions don’t feel like much in the moment, but they compound throughout the day, leaving you exhausted by 3 PM even though you feel like you haven’t accomplished much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The developers who’ve figured this out—the ones who seem to breeze through complex projects—aren’t relying on tricks or shortcuts. They’re leaning on &lt;strong&gt;habits&lt;/strong&gt; that remove these daily friction points. They reuse patterns that work. They automate the repetitive stuff. They keep their tools organized and sharp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news? These aren’t secret techniques that take years to master. They’re practical habits you can start adopting today. Some will save you five minutes here and there. Others will save you hours every week. Together, they compound into a workflow that feels effortless and keeps you focused on actually solving problems instead of fighting your environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are &lt;strong&gt;10 habits&lt;/strong&gt; that will genuinely save you time every single day. Pick a couple to start with, make them stick, then add more. You don’t need to overhaul your entire workflow overnight—small improvements add up faster than you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-build-and-use-a-snippet-library&quot;&gt;1. Build and Use a Snippet Library&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Rewriting the same error handlers, validation, or logging patterns eats up time and introduces inconsistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Save these patterns into a snippet library. Tag them by language (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;js&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;py&lt;/code&gt;) or domain (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;db&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;auth&lt;/code&gt;) so you can recall them instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# ${your_code_here}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;logger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Error: {e}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; Tools like &lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt; make searching and inserting these snippets lightning fast—without breaking flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-standardize-with-templates&quot;&gt;2. Standardize with Templates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Every new module or component starts with the same boilerplate. Doing it by hand is wasted effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Use templates for React components, API routes, or unit tests. You’ll save setup time and keep your codebase consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example React template:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-javascript highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;React&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&apos;react&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;default&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ComponentName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}({})&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;div&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ComponentName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;works&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sr&quot;&gt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Store it once → reuse it forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-automate-file-and-folder-creation&quot;&gt;3. Automate File and Folder Creation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Creating directories, configs, and starter files manually slows you down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Use CLI generators (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ng generate component&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rails g scaffold&lt;/code&gt;) or pair templates with a snippet tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; Keep your templates in CodeMenu, then paste them wherever needed—no need to memorize every CLI flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-document-as-you-go&quot;&gt;4. Document as You Go&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Leaving documentation for “later” often means it never happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Write docstrings, inline comments, or README snippets at the same time you write code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example in Python:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;calculate_tax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;amount&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;
    Calculate tax for a given amount.
    Args:
        amount (float): The income or purchase amount.
    Returns:
        float: The tax due.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bonus: Save comment/docstring templates as snippets so you always follow the same structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-master-keyboard-shortcuts&quot;&gt;5. Master Keyboard Shortcuts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Every time you reach for the mouse, you lose momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Learn IDE, terminal, and snippet manager shortcuts. Add one new shortcut to your muscle memory each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VS Code: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Cmd+Shift+P&lt;/code&gt; → open command palette.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CodeMenu: Global shortcut → instant snippet search, no window-switching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-reuse-proven-solutions&quot;&gt;6. Reuse Proven Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Developers often re-solve problems they’ve already cracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Before coding, ask:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did I solve this before?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there a library or snippet that covers it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you find a solid solution, add it to your snippet/tooling library so you never waste that effort again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-keep-your-tools-organized&quot;&gt;7. Keep Your Tools Organized&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; A messy library (snippets, bookmarks, repos) makes tools harder to use, so you stop using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Spend 10 minutes weekly organizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tag snippets (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;validation&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;db&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delete duplicates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rename cryptic titles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CodeMenu, this takes minutes, and pays off every time you search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-batch-small-tasks&quot;&gt;8. Batch Small Tasks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Context switching kills flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Collect small tasks into a batch list. Handle them in one block instead of sprinkling them through your deep-work hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Answer 5 PR comments together.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write all TODO cleanups before stand-up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update snippets at the end of the week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-version-your-snippets&quot;&gt;9. Version Your Snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Snippets evolve over time. Without versioning, teams diverge into conflicting patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Store shared snippets in Git or a snippet server. Review changes like normal code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tooling:&lt;/strong&gt; Extiri’s &lt;strong&gt;Snippets Store&lt;/strong&gt; (self-hostable) works well with CodeMenu, giving your team one source of truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-schedule-productivity-maintenance&quot;&gt;10. Schedule “Productivity Maintenance”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Your workflow gets bloated unless you prune and refine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Habit:&lt;/strong&gt; Once a week, spend 15 minutes maintaining:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delete unused snippets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve one template.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn a new shortcut.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean up your workspace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of it as “spring cleaning” for your dev environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving time as a developer comes down to habits you repeat daily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a snippet library&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standardize with templates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automate setup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Document as you go&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reuse solutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay organized&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Batch tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Version snippets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maintain weekly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👉 Start with 2 habits this week. Once they’re second nature, add more. Small improvements compound into hours saved every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a tool to make snippets and templates painless, give &lt;a href=&quot;https://extiri.com/codemenu.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CodeMenu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a try—it turns many of these habits into effortless defaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-day-starter-checklist-do-one-per-day&quot;&gt;7-day starter checklist (do one per day)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1: Save three snippets you use daily into your snippet manager and tag them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 2: Create one template for a common file type (React component, test file, or module).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 3: Add a keyboard shortcut for your snippet manager to insert snippets without leaving the editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 4: Batch three small tasks and handle them in one focused block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 5: Audit your snippet library for duplicates and rename unclear items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 6: Version one snippet in Git (or export your snippet tool library) so it’s tracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 7: Teach a teammate one shortcut or snippet workflow (sharing solidifies habit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note on tooling: the suggestions above work with many snippet tools; CodeMenu is one example that supports quick insertion and tagging—feel free to substitute your preferred tool.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/ten-developer-habits</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/ten-developer-habits</guid>
        
        <category>productivity</category>
        
        <category>snippets</category>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introducing Chitneek for iOS - Hear Your Documents, Simply and Privately</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;Do you want a reading app that’s clean, reliable, and doesn’t force you to sign up for everything? Meet &lt;strong&gt;Chitneek&lt;/strong&gt;, the iPhone app that turns PDFs, EPUBs, web pages, notes, Gutenberg classics, and RSS feeds into spoken text — without cloud uploads or unnecessary complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-can-do-with-chitneek&quot;&gt;What You Can Do with Chitneek&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/chitneek-screenshots/Screenshot-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Read PDFs, EPUBs, websites and text&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listen to PDFs, EPUBs, and notes&lt;/strong&gt; using native iOS text-to-speech voices — nothing fancy needed, just clear and dependable reading.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Convert text or web pages into PDFs&lt;/strong&gt; so you can listen later whenever it suits you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access Project Gutenberg right inside the app&lt;/strong&gt; — public domain books are just a tap away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subscribe to RSS feeds&lt;/strong&gt; and have the latest posts delivered for you to listen to.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organize your library&lt;/strong&gt; with named groups, and bookmarks so you can easily find where you left off.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customize playback&lt;/strong&gt;: adjust speed and pitch per document or book to match your listening style.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CarPlay integration&lt;/strong&gt; so you can keep your eyes on the road while listening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep timer&lt;/strong&gt; to stop playback automatically — perfect for nighttime listening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All local storage &amp;amp; usage&lt;/strong&gt;: your files remain on your device; you’re in control of your data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-chitneek-special&quot;&gt;What Makes Chitneek Special&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/chitneek-screenshots/Screenshot-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Keep you collection organized&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitneek isn’t trying to be every kind of reader-app out there — instead, it focuses on doing a few things very well, in a way that feels natural:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimal friction, maximum focus&lt;/strong&gt; — no signups, no cloud dependencies, no uploading.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built-in sources&lt;/strong&gt; like Gutenberg and RSS reduce manual importing and help you access content you care about faster.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple yet powerful organization&lt;/strong&gt; with groups and bookmarks — because locating what you want should be quick.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible audio controls&lt;/strong&gt; which can be adapted to your listening pace and preference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy and peace of mind&lt;/strong&gt; — your documents stay yours, stored locally. No mystery about where your text goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-youll-want-chitneek&quot;&gt;Why You’ll Want Chitneek&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/chitneek-screenshots/Screenshot-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Listen to blog feeds&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of these sound familiar, Chitneek may be exactly what you’ve been looking for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You read often, but want to rest your eyes — or want to listen during walks, commuting, or chores.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You follow blogs or websites and wish for hands-free listening to new content.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You love classic books or public domain works and want easy access without hunting for files.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You care about privacy, offline reliability, and simplicity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-started&quot;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/chitneek-screenshots/Screenshot-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Find interesting books quickly&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download &lt;strong&gt;Chitneek — Read Aloud&lt;/strong&gt; from the App Store.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open the app.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Browse Gutenberg works or add RSS feeds. Import any PDFs or EPUBs you already have.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tap to play, adjust speed/pitch, use the sleep timer or CarPlay when needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organize using groups to keep things tidy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitneek is for anyone who believes that reading aloud should be easy, private, and dependable. If you’ve been looking for a calm, uncluttered experience that still covers everything essential — this is it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/introducing-chitneek</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/introducing-chitneek</guid>
        
        <category>extiri</category>
        
        <category>app-showcase</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From Theory to Practice: 5 Platforms That Turn Learning Into Doing</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;Ever feel stuck in &lt;em&gt;tutorial hell&lt;/em&gt; - watching endless videos but never actually applying what you learn? I’ve been there too. Books and courses are fantastic - they give structure, context, and explanations - but real understanding often comes when you &lt;em&gt;actually do it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, I’ve discovered several platforms that take concepts from theory to hands-on experience. Each one is free and ready to help you practice and internalize what you learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-cryptohack--experiment-with-cryptography&quot;&gt;1. CryptoHack – Experiment with Cryptography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/cryptohack-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;CryptoHack&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cryptography has always fascinated me. Recently, I wanted a way to practice it beyond reading theory, and that’s when I found &lt;strong&gt;CryptoHack&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CryptoHack offers challenges that let you experiment directly with cryptographic algorithms. From XOR operations to RSA attacks, you get to see how the theory works in practice. They also have structured introductory courses if you want guided learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptohack.org&quot;&gt;Explore CryptoHack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-iximiuz-labs--hands-on-devops&quot;&gt;2. iximiuz Labs – Hands-On DevOps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/ixizmuz-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;iximiuz Labs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often learn Linux or Docker from blogs or books - but the moment it clicks is when I actually spin it up. That’s where &lt;strong&gt;iximiuz Labs&lt;/strong&gt; comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This platform provides practical challenges in Linux, Docker, and Kubernetes. Each challenge is designed to let you solve real-world tasks, deepening your understanding of the concepts while keeping it safe in a sandboxed environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://labs.iximiuz.com/challenges&quot;&gt;Try iximiuz Labs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-deep-ml--understand-machine-learning-from-the-inside&quot;&gt;3. Deep-ML – Understand Machine Learning From the Inside&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/deepml-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Deep-ML&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about PCA, neural networks, or gradient descent is one thing - but implementing them yourself is where understanding solidifies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deep-ML&lt;/strong&gt; offers machine learning and deep learning challenges crafted to make you code the algorithms yourself. It’s a structured playground that helps you see how the math and theory translate into real computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deep-ml.com&quot;&gt;Start with Deep-ML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-webgpu-puzzles--feel-parallel-execution&quot;&gt;4. WebGPU Puzzles – Feel Parallel Execution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/wgpupuzzles-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;WebGPU Puzzles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GPU programming can feel abstract until you run code yourself. &lt;strong&gt;WebGPU Puzzles&lt;/strong&gt; brings WGSL coding directly to your browser, no installation required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through small compute puzzles, you dispatch GPU threads and see parallel execution in action. It’s a surprisingly intuitive way to get a tactile feel for GPU computing fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gpupuzzles.answer.ai&quot;&gt;Explore WebGPU Puzzles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-project-euler--sharpen-your-mathematical-thinking&quot;&gt;5. Project Euler – Sharpen Your Mathematical Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/projecteuler-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Project Euler&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about algorithms is useful - but solving them is transformative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Euler&lt;/strong&gt; offers small, elegant math-and-programming problems that make you think algorithmically. I use it especially to train my mathematical thinking, and each solved problem feels like a small victory that reinforces the concepts I’ve learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://projecteuler.net&quot;&gt;Try Project Euler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hands-on-learning-matters&quot;&gt;Hands-On Learning Matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books, blogs, and courses give you the foundation. Hands-on practice turns that knowledge into skill. These platforms have helped me solidify concepts, see results instantly, and stay motivated by giving tangible accomplishments along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope they do the same for you. Dive in, experiment, fail, fix, and learn - your brain will thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://extiri.com/blog/posts/from-theory-to-practice</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://extiri.com/blog/posts/from-theory-to-practice</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>studying</category>
        
        <category>resources</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
